<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The abridgment of Camden's Brita[n]nia with the maps of the seuerall shires of England and Wales.</title>
            <title>Britannia. English. Abridgments</title>
            <author>Camden, William, 1551-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 197 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B11942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107395</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843096</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843096</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177548</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B11942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177548)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1060:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The abridgment of Camden's Brita[n]nia with the maps of the seuerall shires of England and Wales.</title>
                  <title>Britannia. English. Abridgments</title>
                  <author>Camden, William, 1551-1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[132] p. : maps  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Bill printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The title page is engraved.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi²  a-c⁴ [A-E]⁴ F-N⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>British Isles --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>British Isles --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The abridgment of Camden's Britan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ia With The Maps of the seuerall Shires of England and Wales.</p>
            <p>EUCLIDE PTOLEMIE</p>
            <p>Printed by Iohn Bill Printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie. 1626.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>engraving of two men, two cherubs, two globes</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:3"/>
            <head>TO HIS MOST SACRED <hi>MAJESTIE.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Diuine Power that inſpired the breath of life into man, infuſed the life of Authoritie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King. This inſpiration maketh man the image of God; that other maketh the King in particular the Lieutenant of God. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore humane right no ſooner ſtileth one with the name of a King, but diuine Heraldrie graceth him with the title of a mortall God, thereby intimating that it is his chiefeſt glory, within the ſphaere of his Royaltie to imitate the ſingular gouernment of that power, whoſe Subſtitute he is, and with whoſe name he is honoured. Now the vnparalleled excellencie of diuine gouernment ouer the world is grounded vpon that diſtinct knowledge which the Creator hath of the nature, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<pb facs="tcp:177548:4"/> and vſe of all creatures ſubiect to his gouernment. And ſurely the readieſt way for an earthly Potentate to make his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment exactly analogicall to that <hi>Jdea,</hi> will be by getting an accurate knowledge of the nature and qualitie of the Land and People ouer which God hath made him his Lieutenant gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. But the <hi>Metropolis</hi> and the <hi>Royall Throne</hi> require ſuch fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quencie of the Soueraignes preſence, that ſuch knowledge can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be gotten by his owne obſeruations. Our Maps therefore (eſpecially being ioyned with diſcreet obſeruations) as they are delightfull unto all, are eſpecially vſefull vnto the King: for by this meanes, though reſiding in his Princely Seat, he may as the eye from the head, contemplate with much delight and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the remoteſt Territories of his Kingdomes. And becauſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of a higher nature take vp the principal of his time, longer Deſcriptions are not for the purpoſe; the more compendious, ſo as accurate, are moſt ſutable to the calling of a King.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:4"/>
            <p>Vpon theſe grounds (moſt dread Soueraigne) am I bold humbly to preſent theſe ſmall Chorographicall Deſcriptions vnto the greatneſſe of your <hi>Maieſtie.</hi> Their compendiouſneſſe will free them from being thought troubleſome or tedious to your <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> and their exactneſſe (I truſt) will gaine them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation. Howſoeuer, ſhadowes they are of your Royaltie, and therefore they deſire that they (as doth that Body which they repreſent) may ſafely repoſe themſelues vnder the wings of your Soueraigntie; To which he commends them, and his loyall ſeruice, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Sacred Maieſties moſt humble, and moſt faithfull deuoted Subiect and Seruant, <hi>IOHN BIL</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all morall knowledge, the knowing of our ſelues; of all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicall, the knowledge of our owne Countrey is the moſt vſefull and profitable. Yet had moſt men rather ſpend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their precious houres in the moſt difficult trifles in the world, than once to enter into themſelues. And moſt Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in Geographie take more delight to contemplate the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and moſt barbarous Countries of the earth, than lightly to examine the Deſcriptions of their owne. So that (as if like thoſe <hi>Lamij</hi> in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> they had eyes abroad, and incloſed them in boxes in their owne homes) they are accurate in the Deſcriptions of the ſmalleſt village in a forraine King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb facs="tcp:177548:6"/> when they ſcarce know how the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of their ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Country is ſituated. The excuſes that are ordinary for this common neglect, are, either that accurate Deſcriptions are wanting, or that they are ſo voluminous, that they are preiudiciall both to time and purſe. But behold (courteous Reader) thou haſt here exhibited vnto thee ſuch exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite compendious Surueyes of thine owne natiue Countrey, as will at once take away theſe excuſes, and eaſe thee of this double grieuance. The Country deſcribed, both in regard of Commodities wherewith it is fraught, and places of note wherewith it is graced, is a perfect epitome of the World; theſe Maps and Deſcriptions are a compleat epitome of it, and therefore in a double regard worthy thy peruſall. And becauſe no Maps can be rightly vnderſtood without ſome inſight in the generall termes or notions of Geographie, I haue prefixed a compendious Delineation of the ſame. If thou readeſt them, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteſt by them, I haue the principall of my deſire; If thou doeſt both, with a candid ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the Labour, I haue it with Intereſt.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction_to_geography">
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A DELINEATION OF</hi> the vniuerſall Notions of Geographie.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Eographie</hi> is a Science which teacheth the deſcription, diſtinction, and dimenſion of the Earth; and according to the common diuiſion, is either generall, or ſpeciall; or (as ſome of our late <hi>Geographers</hi> haue more fitly diuided it) it is either <hi>Sphaericall,</hi> or <hi>Topographicall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Generall</hi> or <hi>Sphaericall</hi> part of this Science is that which ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth forth the naturall conſtitution of the <hi>Terreſtriall Globe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Terreſtriall Globe</hi> is a round body comprehended within the ſuperficies of earth and water, and ſituated in reſpect of the other Globes or Starres of the world, according to <hi>Ptolemy</hi> and <hi>Tycho Brahe,</hi> in the Center; but according to <hi>Copernicus,</hi> betweene the Orbes of MARS and VENVS.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:7"/>
            <p>The parts whereof it conſiſteth, are either
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Reall,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Imaginarie.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reall,</hi> are ſuch as agree to the <hi>Terreſtriall Globe</hi> by nature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imaginarie,</hi> are ſuch as agree to it by vertue of our vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reall</hi> parts of the <hi>Inferiour Globe</hi> are
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Earth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Water.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Imaginarie</hi> parts are certaine lines which are not, but (for the better vnderſtanding of this Science) are ſuppoſed to be in the Earth.</p>
            <p>Theſe are either
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Straight,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Circular.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> and of this kinde is only one, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Axell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Axell</hi> is a ſtrait line paſſing thorow the middeſt or center of the Earth, the extremeſt points whereof are termed <hi>Poles:</hi> the North point is called the <hi>Articke Pole,</hi> and the South the <hi>Antarticke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Circular Lines</hi> are diuided into the
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Greater,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Leſſer.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Greater Circles</hi> are ſuch as diuide the Globe into two equall parts, each whereof contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in it 360 Degrees, euery Degree being 60 miles; ſo that the Earth by this computation is 21600 Engliſh miles about, and almoſt 7000 miles thorow.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Greater Circles</hi> are three in number,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Meridian,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Horizon,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aequator.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe are either
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mutable, viz.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Immutable,</hi> as the <hi>Aequator.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> with the mutation of the place, as
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Meridian,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Horizon.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:7"/>
            <p>The <hi>Meridian</hi> is a <hi>Circle</hi> drawne by the <hi>Poles</hi> of the world, and the verticall point of the place. Of theſe (though the number ſet downe in the <hi>Artificiall Globe</hi> at the moſt be but 180) are there to be ſuppoſed in the <hi>Reall Globe</hi> as many as there are <hi>Zeniths</hi> or verticall points from Eaſt to Weſt. So places diſtant Eaſt and Weſt haue diuers <hi>Meridians,</hi> (and in this reſpect it is called a <hi>Mutable Circle</hi>) but places different directly North and South haue the ſame.</p>
            <p>Among theſe one is of ſpeciall note and uſe, which <hi>Geographers</hi> commonly call the firſt and chiefe <hi>Meridian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Meridian</hi> is that from which the longitude of places from Weſt to Eaſt is reckoned. This <hi>Meridian</hi> (according to <hi>Ptolemie</hi> and the Ancients) paſſeth thorow the <hi>Canary Ilands,</hi> but according to our latter Artiſts, vpon better reaſons, thorow the <hi>Azores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Horizon</hi> is a Circle comprehending al that ſpace of the Earth which is viſible, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth it from the reſt which lieth vnder and is inuiſible.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Horizon</hi> is either
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Senſible,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rationall.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Senſible Horizon</hi> is the Circle that terminateth a mans ken looking round about him in an open place; and therefore is greater or leſſer, according to the conueniencie of the place wherein a man ſtandeth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Rationall Horizon</hi> is a Circle paſſing by the Center of the Earth, whoſe two Poles are the point directly ouer a mans head, which is called the <hi>Zenith,</hi> and the point directly vnder his feet, called the <hi>Nadyr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Rationall Horizon</hi> is that which Geographers reckon among the greater Circles, and not the <hi>Senſible;</hi> but both change according to the change of the place which way ſoeuer it is.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this is to diſcerne the diuers riſings and ſettings of the Starres.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:8"/>
            <p>The <hi>Aequator</hi> is a great Circle paſſing thorow the midſt of the Earth, and diuiding it exactly into two equall parts or <hi>Haemiſpheres,</hi> North and South. The vſe of it is to ſhew the latitude of any place; for from it both the Southerne latitude betwixt it and the South Pole, and the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne latitude betwixt it and the North Pole is to be reckoned.</p>
            <p>The leſſer Circles or parallels, are either
<list>
                  <item>named with pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar names, as
<list>
                        <item>the Tropicks of
<list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Cancer.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Capricorne.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Polar Circles.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>want ſuch, and they are commonly called <hi>Parallels.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Tropicks</hi> are <hi>Parallels</hi> bounding the Sunnes greateſt declination, which is either toward the North, and from the Celeſtiall Signe is called <hi>The Tropicke of Cancer;</hi> or towards the South, and is from another Signe called <hi>The Tropicke of Capricorne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both of theſe are 23 degrees diſtant from the <hi>Aequinoctiall,</hi> the one Southward, and the other Northward.</p>
            <p>The Polar Circles are <hi>Parallels</hi> compaſſing the <hi>Poles.</hi> That which compaſſeth the <hi>North Pole</hi> is termed from the ſigne of the Beare the <hi>Arcticke Circle;</hi> that which compaſſeth the <hi>South Pole</hi> is termed the <hi>Antarcticke Circle,</hi> becauſe it is iuſt oppoſite to the former.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Parallel</hi> compaſſeth the Earth from Eaſt to Weſt, and diuideth it into two vnequall parts.</p>
            <p>Theſe foure nominated <hi>Parallels</hi> or leſſer Circles ſerue to deſcribe the <hi>Zones</hi> ſo much mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the writings of Ancients; the vnnamed <hi>Parallels</hi> to ſet out <hi>Climates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Zone</hi> is a ſpace of earth contained betwixt two leſſer Circles: the number of them is fiue, whereof two are ouer-cold, one ouer-hot, and two temperate.</p>
            <p>The two ouer-cold <hi>Zones</hi> are thoſe parts of the Earth which lie betwixt the two Polar Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and the <hi>Poles.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:8"/>
            <p>The two temperate <hi>Zones</hi> are betwixt the <hi>Tropicks</hi> of <hi>Cancer</hi> and the <hi>Articke,</hi> and betwixt the <hi>Tropicke</hi> of <hi>Capricorne</hi> and the <hi>Antarticke</hi> Circles.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Torrid</hi> or ouer-hot <hi>Zone</hi> is that which lieth betwixt both the <hi>Tropicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both the <hi>Torrid</hi> and <hi>Frigid Zones</hi> (though the Ancients thought them to be altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitable) are in many parts at this day well inhabited.</p>
            <p>Againe, the Inhabitants in the burnt <hi>Zones</hi> are called <hi>Amphiſcians,</hi> for that they haue the meridian ſhadow on both ſides of them, ſome part of the yeere Northwards, and ſometimes Southwards. In the temperate <hi>Zones, Hetoroſcians,</hi> hauing the ſhadow but on one ſide; and the frigid <hi>Periſcians</hi> hauing their ſhadowes runne round about.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Inhabitants in the ſame parallel and oppoſite part of the Meridian are called <hi>Periaecians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the like parrallel on the other ſide of the line and ſame meridian <hi>Antiaecians.</hi> In the like pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel on the other ſide of the line and oppoſite part of the meridian, <hi>Antipodes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A climate is a ſpace of earth contained betwixt two parallels, diſtant from the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> towards the North or South Pole: the vſe of climats is to diſtinguiſh the length and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the daies in all places, for places as they differ North and South, ſo haue they vnequall daies and nights; the more Northerly climats and places hauing longer daies in the Summer, and longer nights in the Winter than the more Southerly doe enioy.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the generall or ſphericall part of <hi>Geography.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſpeciall or Topographicall part hereof is that which ſetteth forth the deſcription of the <hi>Terreſtriall Globe</hi> ſo farre forth as it is diuided into diſtinct parts or places, and is either
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>The deſcription of ſome great integrating part of the Earth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Or of ſome one Region, and ſo it is properly termed Chorography.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177548:9"/>
                  <item>3 <hi>Or of ſome particular place in a Region.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>According to the greater integrating parts thereof, the Ancients diuided the whole world into three parts (no more being then diſcouered) namely <hi>Aſia, Africa,</hi> and <hi>Europa;</hi> but now of late all the world being in a manner found out, the reſt is diuided into other three parts <hi>(viz.) Atlantis,</hi> or <hi>America Septentrionall, Meridionall,</hi> and <hi>Terra del Chaſdi</hi> or the <hi>South Continent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſia</hi> is bounded on the North with the <hi>Hyperborean</hi> Seas, on the Eaſt with <hi>Mar del Zur</hi> or South Sea, on the South with the <hi>Indian</hi> Seas, and on the Weſt with the Red Sea, part of the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea, the <hi>Heleſpont,</hi> and the Riuers <hi>Don</hi> and <hi>Duyna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Africa</hi> is enuironed with the <hi>Midland</hi> Seas North, the Red Sea Eaſt, and the <hi>Aethiopian</hi> and <hi>Atlantick</hi> Ocean, on the South and Weſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Europe</hi> is bordered on the Eaſt with <hi>Don</hi> and <hi>Duyna,</hi> on the North with the Frozen Seas, on the Weſt with the <hi>Atlantick</hi> Ocean, and on the South with the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>North America</hi> is termined on the Eaſt with the North-Sea, on the Weſt with the South-Sea, on the North with the <hi>Hyperborean</hi> or Frozen-Seas, and on the South with the <hi>Iſthmos</hi> at <hi>Panania.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>South America</hi> is confined on the North with this <hi>Iſthmos,</hi> on the South with the Straights of <hi>Magellane,</hi> on the Eaſt with the <hi>Aethiopian</hi> Sea, and on the Weſt with <hi>Mar del Zur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>South Continent</hi> is accoſted on the North with <hi>Mar del Zur,</hi> the <hi>Aethiopick,</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> Seas. But how it is on the other parts is not yet diſcouered.</p>
            <p>Each of theſe more ſpatious parts is againe ſubdiuided into many Regions, as <hi>Aſia</hi> is diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into theſe Regions, <hi>Chyna, Tartaria, Muſcouia, Georgia, Armenia, Natolia, Syria, Caldea, Arabia, Perſia, Magora, India,</hi> and <hi>Cauchychina,</hi> with innumerable Iſlands called the <hi>Moluccoes</hi> or <hi>Spicerie</hi> Iſlands and <hi>Iapan,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Africa</hi> into <hi>Aegypt, Abyſsina, Monomotapa, Magadoxo, Quiloa, Mozambigue, Manicongo, Guynea, Byledulgerid, Barbarie, Cyrenaica,</hi> and <hi>Nubia,</hi> with the Iſlands of the <hi>Canaryes, Cape-verde, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Helen,</hi> and <hi>Madagaſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Europe</hi> into theſe Kingdomes, <hi>Crymea, Polon, Sweden, Denmarke, Germanie,</hi> both the higher and lower, <hi>Greece, Hungarie, Bohemia, Auſtria, Italy, France, Spaine,</hi> with the Iſlands of <hi>Candy, Corſica, Sardinia, Maiorca,</hi> and theſe moſt famous Iſlands of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>North America</hi> into <hi>Noua Britannia, Noua Albion, Noua Anglia, Virginia, Noua Francia, Florida, Calfornia, Noua Granada, Noua Hiſpania, Nicoragua,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>South America</hi> into <hi>Caſtilia del-Oro, Peru, Chily, Guiana, Ouram, Chicas, Braſilia,</hi> and <hi>Pantagones,</hi> with the <hi>Antellar Iles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>South Continent</hi> (ſo farre as is diſcouered) into <hi>Noua Guinea, Luchach, Maletur,</hi> with the Iſlands of <hi>Salomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe euery one of theſe Regions is ſubdiuided into Prouinces, Hundreds, or Counties. Theſe three kinde of parts make vp the perfect ſubiect of <hi>Topographie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe euery part and place of the earth is conſidered either
<list>
                  <item>in it ſelfe.</item>
                  <item>according to its adiuncts.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In it ſelfe, and ſo it is
<list>
                  <item>Continent</item>
                  <item>Iland.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>A Continent is a great quantitie of land in which many kingdomes and principalities are conioyned together, none of them being ſeparated from the reſt by any Sea.</p>
            <p>An Iſland (<hi>quaſi</hi> an eie of land, called in Latine, <hi>Inſula quaſi in ſalo</hi>) is a part of land com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed and enuironed round about with waters, of which <hi>Great Britaine</hi> and <hi>Iapan</hi> are the moſt ſpacious.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:10"/>
            <p>Theſe againe are obſeruable parts both of Continents and Iſlands,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Peninſula.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſthmus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Promontorium.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peninſula (quaſi pene Inſula)</hi> is a tract of land, which being compaſſed almoſt round with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, is ioyned by ſome little necke or <hi>Iſthmus</hi> to the firme land, as <hi>Peloponeſus</hi> in Greece.</p>
            <p>An <hi>Iſthmus</hi> is a narrow peece of land which ioyneth the <hi>Peninſula</hi> to the Continent or grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Iſlands, as the ſtraights of <hi>Dariene</hi> and <hi>Corinth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Promontorium</hi> is a high mountaine ſhooting it ſelfe much farther into the Sea than the Adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent land. The extremeſt point or nooke hereof is called a <hi>Cape,</hi> as <hi>Cape-verde</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The adiuncts of a place are either ſuch as reſpect
<list>
                  <item>the earth it ſelfe.</item>
                  <item>the heauens.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that agree to a place in reſpect of the earth, are three in number, viz.
<list>
                  <item>1 The magnitude or extent of a Country.</item>
                  <item>2 The bounds and limits.</item>
                  <item>3 The qualitie.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The magnitude comprehendeth the length and bredth of any place. The length of a place is meaſured Eaſt and Weſt, what figure ſoeuer the place is of; the bredth thereof North and South.</p>
            <p>It is to be obſerued that thoſe places that are vnder the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> haue no bredth, becauſe that the meaſuring of latitude is begunne from this circle.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The bounds of a Country is a line terminating it round about, and diſtinguiſhing it from the bordering lands or waters.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The qualitie of a place is the naturall temper and diſpoſition thereof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:10"/>
            <p>A place in regard of the heauens is either
<list>
                  <item>Eaſt.</item>
                  <item>Weſt.</item>
                  <item>North.</item>
                  <item>South.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe places are properly ſaid to be Northerne, which lie betwixt the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> and the <hi>Arctick</hi> Pole. Thoſe Southerne, which are betwixt the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> and the <hi>Antarcticke</hi> Pole.</p>
            <p>Thoſe places likewiſe are ſaid to be Eaſterne which lie in the Eaſterne <hi>Haemiſphaere,</hi> termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the firſt Meridian which paſſeth thorow the <hi>Azores,</hi> and thoſe the Weſterne which lie within the <hi>Haemiſphaere</hi> which lieth Weſternly of the ſame Meridian. And thus much of the vniuerſall Notions of <hi>Geography.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="England" type="region">
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:11"/>
            <div type="map">
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of England</figDesc>
                     <head>A TIPE OF ENGLAND</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="description">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:11"/>
               <head>OF ENGLAND.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His farre famouſed Kingdome is bordered on the North with <hi>Scotland,</hi> on the South with the Britiſh Sea, on the Eaſt with the German Ocean, and on the Weſt with the Hybernian Seas. It is ſituate in the temperate <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne</hi> and eighth <hi>Climate;</hi> watered with a multitude of Cryſtall ſtreames, Currents, and Nauigable Riuers; the banks whereof are crowned with Flowrie Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, the Meadowes repleniſhed with abundance of Cattell, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſted with all manner of fertile fields, of all manner of Corne and Graine; and beſides all theſe affords many other both Commodities and Rarities, which hereafter are particularly expreſſed in their proper places.</p>
               <p>This kingdome was firſt inhabited by ſome Colonies which tranſplanted themſelues from the neighbouring coaſts of <hi>France</hi> &amp; <hi>Lower Germanie,</hi> as the affinity of their Language, Policie, Religion, and Manners, doe vnqueſtionably proue; being the ofspring of <hi>Gomer</hi> of <hi>Iaphets</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genie, as their owne appellation doth witneſſe, calling themſelues <hi>Komery,</hi> who poſſeſſed and gouerned this Iland aboue one thouſand yeares. About fifty foure yeares before the Natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our Lord and Sauiour, <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> entred this land, which within one hundred and fifty yeares after was ſubiugated by the <hi>Romans,</hi> vnder whoſe commands they liued till the 430 yeare after Chriſt, when the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire declining, was forced to call home their Garriſons, and hauing before exhauſted the ſtrength of this Kingdome, left it a prey to the enemie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb facs="tcp:177548:12"/> the <hi>Picts</hi> aſſaulting this land thus disfurniſhed &amp; weakned, they were compelled to craue the aid of the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Anglies,</hi> a warlike nation, inhabiting neare the confines of <hi>Denmarke;</hi> who being ariued, chaſed away their enemies; and allured with the temperature, fertilitie and pleaſantneſſe of the Country (flowing in great numbers) expelled the <hi>Britaines</hi> or <hi>Komeros,</hi> that would not liue vnder their lawes and ſubiection, and ſo held it till the yeare 1066. when <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour with his <hi>Normans</hi> ſubdued them, whoſe ſucceſſors haue continually en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed it to this preſent time.</p>
               <p>It was anciently diuided by the <hi>Romans</hi> into three parts, <hi>Britanniam primam,</hi> from the South parts to <hi>Trent; Maximam Caeſarienſem,</hi> from thence Northward; and <hi>Britanniam ſecundam,</hi> which we call <hi>Wales.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After by the <hi>Saxons</hi> it was diuided into an Heptarchie, which at laſt (reduced to a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie) was by <hi>Elfred</hi> diuided into Shires, Wapentakes, and Tithings; with Iuſtices and Sheriffes appointed for miniſtring of iuſtice, which partly confirmed, partly altered by <hi>William</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, was at laſt diuided into 39 Shires of the Engliſh, with the addition of 13 of <hi>Wales.</hi> In which are at this preſent two famous Vniuerſities, the Seminaries of vertue and learning; 26 Biſhopricks, 641 Market Towees, 186 Caſtles, 9725 Pariſh Churches, 555 Riuers, 956 Bridges, 13 Chaſes, 68 Foreſts, and 781 Parkes. Tribunalls, or Courts of iuſtice tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, nine, <hi>viz.</hi> Parliament, Starchamber, Chancerie, Kings Bench, Exchequer, Common pleas, Court of Wards, Admiraltie, and Court of Requeſts, beſides Court Leet and Baron. Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſeuen, of Conuocation, Synods, Audience, Arches, Prerogatiue, Faculties, and Peculiar Iuriſdictions. Rankes of Nobilitie nine, that is, Dukes, Marqueſſes, Earles, Viſcounts, Barons, Baronets, Knights, Eſquires, and Gentlemen. And of Inferiour Ranke or Communaltie three, Yeomen, Husbandmen, and Tradeſmen.</p>
               <p>The Battells by Sea and Land ſince the Conqueſt, fought by the Kings, Nobilitie, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, againſt forraine inuaſions, and Domeſtique and Inteſtine warres, 76. The laſt and moſt Admirable, being in the Chaſe of the <hi>Spaniſh Armado,</hi> Ann. Dom. 1588.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="tabular_description_of_the_Spanish_Armada">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:12"/>
               <head>¶ A Table containing the prouiſions of the <hi>Spaniſh Armado</hi> againſt ENGLAND in <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1588. and <hi>Anno</hi> ELIZ. REGINae XXX.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Leaders.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Prouinces aiding.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Galliaſſes and Gallions.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Ships and Hulks.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Pinaces and Carauals.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Great Ordnance</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Saylers.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Souldiers.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Galley-ſlaues.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>D. Medina Sydonia.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Portugal.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>300</cell>
                        <cell>1300</cell>
                        <cell>3300</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Diego de Mandranae.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Portugal.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>360</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>888</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Io. Martynes de Richaldes</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Biſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>250</cell>
                        <cell>700</cell>
                        <cell>2000</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Michael de Oquendo.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Guiapuſco.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>310</cell>
                        <cell>700</cell>
                        <cell>2000</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Pedro de Valdez.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Andolozia.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>280</cell>
                        <cell>800</cell>
                        <cell>2400</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Martyn de Vertendona.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Italie.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>310</cell>
                        <cell>800</cell>
                        <cell>2000</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Diego Floris de Valdez.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Caſtile.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>380</cell>
                        <cell>1700</cell>
                        <cell>2400</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Iohn Lopez de Medina.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Medina.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>400</cell>
                        <cell>700</cell>
                        <cell>3200</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Hugo de Moncade.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Naples.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                        <cell>460</cell>
                        <cell>870</cell>
                        <cell>1200</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Antonio Buccade.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Mendoza.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>193</cell>
                        <cell>574</cell>
                        <cell>488</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="notes">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>ESPECIALL NOTES</hi> worthy of obſeruation.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>13 <hi>H.</hi> 1. The firſt Parliament was in <hi>Anno</hi> 1112</item>
                  <item>19 <hi>H.</hi> 2. Ireland was conquered in <hi>Anno</hi> 1172</item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Ioh.</hi> Normandy was loſt by King Iohn and the title thereto releaſed <hi>Anno</hi> 1202</item>
                  <item>43 <hi>H.</hi> 3. Normandy was loſt by King Iohn and the title thereto releaſed <hi>Anno</hi> 1258</item>
                  <item>11 <hi>E.</hi> 1. Wales was ſubdued <hi>Anno</hi> 1283</item>
                  <item>19 <hi>E.</hi> 3. The order of the Garter deuiſed <hi>Anno</hi> 1344</item>
                  <item>14 <hi>E.</hi> 3. England firſt quartered the Armes of France <hi>Anno</hi> 1339</item>
                  <item>21 <hi>E.</hi> 3. Calice was wonne in <hi>Anno</hi> 1346</item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Mariae.</hi> Calice was loſt <hi>Anno</hi> 1557</item>
                  <item>5 <hi>H.</hi> 5. Normandy was wonne in <hi>Anno</hi> 1416</item>
                  <item>8 <hi>H.</hi> 5. King <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth was proclaimed heire Apparant and Regent of France in <hi>Anno</hi> 1419</item>
                  <item>10 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth was crowned King of France in the Citie of Paris <hi>Anno</hi> 1431</item>
                  <item>27 <hi>H.</hi> 6. France was loſt in <hi>Anno</hi> 1449</item>
                  <item>28 <hi>H.</hi> 6. Normandy was loſt in <hi>Anno</hi> 1449</item>
                  <item>31 <hi>H.</hi> 6. Acuitaine &amp;c. were loſt in <hi>Anno</hi> 1453</item>
                  <item>4 <hi>R.</hi> 2. Wat Tylors Rebellion <hi>Anno</hi> 1380</item>
                  <item>29 <hi>H.</hi> 6. Iack Cades Rebellion <hi>Anno</hi> 1450</item>
                  <item>4 <hi>H.</hi> 8. Nauarre ſurpriſed by the Spaniards <hi>Anno</hi> 1512</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="list">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:13"/>
               <head>At the time of the firſt diſſoluing of Religious Houſes <hi>in</hi> ENGLAND <hi>there were</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>ARchbiſhopricks and Biſhopricks 21</item>
                  <item>Deanries 11</item>
                  <item>Archdeaconries 60</item>
                  <item>Dignities and Prebends in Cathedrall Churches 364</item>
                  <item>Benefices 8803</item>
                  <item>Religious Houſes 65</item>
                  <item>Hoſpitalls 110</item>
                  <item>Colledges 96</item>
                  <item>Chauntries and free Chappells 2374</item>
                  <item>Their Rates were <hi>per annum</hi> 320180</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="table">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:14"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" cols="4">In the Prouince of <hi>Canterbury,</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Dioceſes</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Pariſh-Churches,</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Churches appropriated</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell rows="22">In the Dioceſe</cell>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Canterbury</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>257</cell>
                        <cell>140</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>London</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>623</cell>
                        <cell>189</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Wincheſter</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>362</cell>
                        <cell>131</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Couentrey</hi> and <hi>Lichfield</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>557</cell>
                        <cell>250</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Salisburie</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>248</cell>
                        <cell>109</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>h</hi> and <hi>Well<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>388</cell>
                        <cell>160</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Lincolne</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1255</cell>
                        <cell>577</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Peterborough</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>293</cell>
                        <cell>91</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Exeter</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>604</cell>
                        <cell>239</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Gloceſter</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>267</cell>
                        <cell>125</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Hereford</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>313</cell>
                        <cell>166</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Norwich</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1121</cell>
                        <cell>385</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Elie</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>141</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Rocheſter</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>98</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Chicheſter</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>250</cell>
                        <cell>112</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Oxford</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>195</cell>
                        <cell>88</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Worceſter</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>241</cell>
                        <cell>76</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Eriſtol</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>236</cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>S. Dauids</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>308</cell>
                        <cell>120</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Bangor</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>107</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Llandeffe</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>177</cell>
                        <cell>98</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>S. Aſaph</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>121</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="total" cols="2">Peculiar in the Prouince of <hi>Canterbury</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="total" cols="2">The ſumme of the Prouince of <hi>Canterbury</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>8219</cell>
                        <cell>3303</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" cols="4">In the Prouince of <hi>Yorke,</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell rows="4">In the Dioceſe</cell>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Yorke</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>581</cell>
                        <cell>336</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Durham</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>135</cell>
                        <cell>87</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Cheſter</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>256</cell>
                        <cell>101</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Of <hi>Carliſle</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>93</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="total" cols="2">The ſumme of the Prouince of <hi>Yorke</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1065</cell>
                        <cell>592</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="total" cols="2">The totall ſumme in both Prouinces,</cell>
                        <cell>9284</cell>
                        <cell>3845</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="list_of_shires">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:14"/>
               <list>
                  <head>Shires in ENGLAND.</head>
                  <item>COrnwall.</item>
                  <item>Deuonſhire.</item>
                  <item>Dorcetſhire.</item>
                  <item>Somerſetſhire.</item>
                  <item>Wiltſhire.</item>
                  <item>Hampſhire.</item>
                  <item>Barkſhire.</item>
                  <item>Surrey.</item>
                  <item>Suſſex.</item>
                  <item>Kent.</item>
                  <item>Middleſex.</item>
                  <item>Eſſex.</item>
                  <item>Hartfordſhire.</item>
                  <item>Buckinghamſhire.</item>
                  <item>Oxfordſhire.</item>
                  <item>Gloceſterſhire.</item>
                  <item>Worceſterſhire.</item>
                  <item>Warwickſhire.</item>
                  <item>Northamptonſhire.</item>
                  <item>Bedfordſhire.</item>
                  <item>Huntingtonſhire.</item>
                  <item>Cambridgeſhire.</item>
                  <item>Suffolke.</item>
                  <item>Northfolke.</item>
                  <item>Lincolneſhire.</item>
                  <item>Rutlandſhire.</item>
                  <item>Leiceſterſhire.</item>
                  <item>Staffordſhire.</item>
                  <item>Darbiſhire.</item>
                  <item>Nottinghamſhire.</item>
                  <item>Yorkeſhire.</item>
                  <item>Durham Biſhoprick.</item>
                  <item>Northumberland.</item>
                  <item>Cumberland.</item>
                  <item>Weſtmerland.</item>
                  <item>Lancaſter.</item>
                  <item>Cheſhire.</item>
                  <item>Shropſhire.</item>
                  <item>Herefordſhire.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Shires in <hi>Wales</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>RAdnorſhire.</item>
                  <item>Brecknockſh.</item>
                  <item>Monmouthſh.</item>
                  <item>Glamorganſhire.</item>
                  <item>Carmardenſhire.</item>
                  <item>Pembrookeſhire.</item>
                  <item>Cardiganſhire.</item>
                  <item>Montgomeriſhire.</item>
                  <item>Merionethſhire.</item>
                  <item>Carnaruanſhire.</item>
                  <item>Angleſey.</item>
                  <item>Denbighſhire.</item>
                  <item>Flintſhire.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="maps_and_descriptions_of_shires">
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:15"/>
            <head>THE MAPS AND DESCRIPTIONS OF THE SEVERALL SHIRES OF <hi>ENGLAND</hi> AND <hi>WALES.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="Devon" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:16"/>
               <head>Deuon-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Euon-ſhire,</hi> which the <hi>Corniſh-Britaines</hi> named <hi>Deuinan,</hi> and the <hi>Welſh-Britaines Duffneint.</hi> ſignifying low Valleys, abbutteth on the Weſt vpon <hi>Cornwall,</hi> being diuided from it by the Riuer <hi>Tamar:</hi> On the South and North ſides it is walled with the Sea, and on the Eaſt with <hi>Sommerſet-ſhire.</hi> The <hi>Dimenſion</hi> being from <hi>Canſhere</hi> North, to <hi>Salcombe</hi> South, 55. Miles, and from <hi>Thornecombe</hi> Eaſt, to <hi>Hartland-point</hi> Weſt, 54. Miles, the compaſſe being about 200. Miles: It is diuided into 33. Hundreds, wherein are contained 394. Pariſh Churches, and it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſperſed with 29. Riuers, being fitted with 166. Bridges. It hath the foundations of 9. notable Religious Houſes and Monaſteries, which now remaine but ruines. It is well traded with 37. Market Townes for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, the principall whereof is the famous Citie of <hi>Exeter,</hi> which is ſeated vpon the Riuer <hi>Ex,</hi> and thereof hath the name: but by <hi>Ptolomy</hi> it was called <hi>Iſea,</hi> and by the <hi>Welſh Pencaer.</hi> It is very pleaſant ſituated on the riſing of a Hill, adorned with ſtately buildings, and is plentifully furniſhed with all kinde of prouiſion, as well for pleaſure as neceſſary vſe. It was compaſſed about by King <hi>Athalſtane,</hi> with a circular wall, except on the ſide towards the Riuer <hi>Ex,</hi> where it is built in a ſtrait line, and is beautified with faire Battlements, diuers Towers, and 6. Gates, for paſſage. On the Eaſt ſide of this Citie ſtands the Caſtle, which in former times was the reſident ſeat of the <hi>Weſt-Saxon</hi> Kings. In it alſo are many faire Churches, but the chiefe is Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> the Cathedrall, which was made a Biſhops Sea by <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor: It is gouerned by a Maior, 24. Brethren, and a Recorder, hauing Latitude 50. 45. degrees, and Longitude degrees 20. 39. This Shire hath many hills and dales, hauing ſtore of woods: And though the ſoile be ſomewhat fruitfull of it ſelfe, yet it is very much amended by the induſtry of the Inhabitants, with the ſand that they fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch from the Sea ſide. The Aire is ſharp and healthfull, the commodities are generally Wooll, Cloth, Kearſies, Lead, Corne, and Cattell, with abundance of Fiſh and Fowle. This Countrey hath many fitter Hauens for inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of ſhips, than <hi>Cornwall,</hi> whereof <hi>Totnes, Plimouth,</hi> and <hi>Dartmouth</hi> are accounted the moſt famous. In <hi>Exmore</hi> in this Shire are ſandy ſtones ſet in diuers formes, ſome circular, and ſome triangle wiſe, which are ſaid to be the ancient memorable markes of Victories obtained there by the <hi>Romans, Saxons,</hi> and <hi>Danes.</hi> And at a place called <hi>Hubſtow,</hi> not farre from the mouth of <hi>Tawe</hi> (in the yeare of Chriſt 879.) was the <hi>Dane Hubba</hi> (who in many places perſecuted the Engliſh) encountred, ſlaine, and buried.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:16"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Devon</figDesc>
                     <head>DEVON SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Dorset" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:17"/>
               <head>Dorſet-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Orſet-ſhirs,</hi> the Inhabitants wherof (by <hi>Ptolomy</hi>) were called <hi>Durotriges,</hi> by the <hi>Brit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ines Dur-Gwgr,</hi> and by the <hi>Engliſh Saxons Dor-Seddar;</hi> It hath <hi>Sommerſet</hi> and <hi>Wilt-ſhires</hi> on the North, <hi>Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n-ſhire</hi> and another part of <hi>Sommerſet-ſhire</hi> on the Weſt, <hi>Hamp-ſhire</hi> on the Eaſt, and the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Seas on the South. It is extended in length 44. Miles, in bredth 24. and makes his circumference about 150. Miles. It is ſhared into fiue diuiſions, viz <hi>Sherborne, Bridport, Shaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r, Dorch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> and <hi>Blanford,</hi> and theſe are ſubdiuided into 34. Hundreds, which containe in them 248. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Churches. It is interlaced with the currents of many cleare and freſh-water Springs, hauing 4. Riuers, and 24. Bridges, &amp; in former times hath beene guarded with 8. ſtrong Caſtles, which time hath now almoſt quite deuoured. It hath entercourſe and traſtique with 8. Market Townes, the principall whereof is <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> which in the <hi>Itinerarium</hi> of <hi>Antoninus</hi> was called <hi>Durnouaria,</hi> ſignifying the <hi>Ferry:</hi> it is ſeated on the South ſide of the Riuer <hi>Frome,</hi> and <hi>Foſſe-way</hi> the <hi>Romane Cawſy.</hi> In times paſt this Towne was walled, and much greater than it is; but by the <hi>Danes</hi> who quite raſed downe the walles, it was brought low, and of a leſſe quantitie. It is now gouerned by two Bayliffes, one Alderman, and a Recorder: The height of the Pole being there 50. 38. degrees for Latitude, and the Longitude 21. 51. degrees. Not farre from this Towne on the South ſide is a ſmall plot of ground raiſed ſome 30. paces higher than the reſt of the Plaine, and compaſſed about with 5. Trenches, containing 10. Acres in quantitie, and is called by the Country people, <hi>The May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Caſtle:</hi> hauing entrance into it but only at the Eaſt &amp; Weſt ſides; it is now tilled, and beareth Corne, but it is thought in times paſt to haue beene ſome fort of defence for the <hi>Roman</hi> Gariſons. The ſoile of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is very fruitfull, producing many neceſſary commodities: the Aire very wholſome, and the ſituation moſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t both for Champion and Woods, hauing in it 2. Forreſts, 12. Parks, and one Chaſe. The chiefe commoditie, being here <hi>Wood, Wooll,</hi> and <hi>Corne.</hi> This Shire hath alſo beene beautified with many faire Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſterie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Religious Houſes, which are now transformed to heaps of Ruines, like that old decayed Caſtle of <hi>Badburg,</hi> which was inuironed with a triple Trench, and had beene ſometime the ſeat of the <hi>Weſt-Saxon</hi> Kings.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:17"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Dorset</figDesc>
                     <head>DORSET SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Somerset" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:18"/>
               <head>Sommerſet-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ommerſet-ſhire</hi> is ſo called of an ancient Towne named <hi>Sommerton,</hi> which in former ages was the chiefeſt and moſt famous in all the County. It is bounded with <hi>Deuon,</hi> and <hi>Dorſet-ſhires</hi> on the South, the Seuerne Sea on the North, <hi>Wilt-ſhire</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire</hi> on the Eaſt and North-eaſt, and <hi>Deuon-ſhire</hi> on the Weſt. The length of it, from <hi>Brackley</hi> Eaſt, to <hi>Oure</hi> Weſt, being 55. Miles; and bredth, from <hi>Chard</hi> South, to <hi>Porſhut-point</hi> North, about 40. Miles, the whole circuit containing much vpon 204. Miles. It is diuided into 42. Hundreds, wherein are 305. Pariſh Churches. It is furniſhed with commodious Hauens and Ports, hauing 9. Riuers, and 45. Bridges. It is ſtrengthened with 4. Caſtles, and hath beene fairely adorned with many Religious Houſes, whereof the Abbey of <hi>Glaſtenburg</hi> was of greateſt note, both for quantitie and quality, the antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie whereof was deduced from <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> whole body (as the report goes) was there interred. So likewiſe was <hi>Witham</hi> Nunnery erected by King <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. and <hi>Hinton,</hi> which were afterwards the firſt and ſecond Houſes of <hi>Carthuſian</hi> Monkes that euer were in <hi>England;</hi> but now with diuers other like, they lie preſſed with their owne ruines. This County is traffiqued with 24. Market Townes, and 3. famous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, namely <hi>Briſtow, Bath,</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> the firſt whereof, though vnequall in bigneſſe to ſome others in <hi>England,</hi> yet for beautie and pleaſant ſituation, will hardly yeeld vnto any. The next is <hi>Bath,</hi> ſo called from the <hi>Hot-Bathes,</hi> and medicinable ſprings, which to the exceeding comfort and wonderfull cures of infinite diſeaſed perſons of all ſorts, by Gods prouidence doe there continually boyle and bubble vp. The third is <hi>Wells,</hi> which (as ſome hold) hath the name from certaine Wells which there ſpring up, inſomuch as in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times that Sea hath beene called <hi>Fontanenſis Eccleſia.</hi> It is gouerned by a Maior, 7. Magiſtrates, 16. Burgeſſes, and a Recorder. The Latitude being there 51. 12. degrees, and the Longitude 21. 36. degrees. This County as it is moſt delightfull in Summer, the Aire being mild, temperate, and pleaſant, yet is it as myry, moiſt, and wet in Winter, inſomuch as it is then exceeding troubleſome for Trauellers. But the ſoile is moſt fruitfull and fertile, yeelding in abundance moſt of our neceſſary commodities: yet chiefly doth it excell for the goodneſſe of Corne, and fatneſſe of Cattell, wherein it exceedeth the moſt of our other Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Neither is it without rich Mines of Lead, which haue beene and are very gainfull to the County; and at Saint <hi>Vincents</hi> Rocke are gotten great ſtore of Diamonds, which for beautie and luſter doe parallel the beſt, but are defectiue in the hardneſſe. In this Shire haue beene fought many bloudy battells, as that neere <hi>Pen,</hi> when King <hi>Canutus</hi> was purſued by <hi>Edmond</hi> named <hi>Ironſide;</hi> and that which was performed by <hi>Ealſtaw</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sherborne</hi> vpon the <hi>Danes,</hi> neare to <hi>Bridge-water,</hi> with diuers others.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:18"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Somerset</figDesc>
                     <head>SOMERSET SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Wiltshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:19"/>
               <head>Wilt-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Iltſhire,</hi> which the old <hi>Engliſh-Saxons</hi> called <hi>Wilſetta,</hi> hath <hi>Barkeſhire</hi> on the Eaſt, <hi>Gloceſter</hi> and <hi>Somerſetſhires</hi> on the Weſt, <hi>Gloceſterſhire</hi> alone on the North, and <hi>Dorſet</hi> and <hi>Hampſhire</hi> on the South. The length from <hi>Burgate</hi> South to <hi>Ingl ſham</hi> North, being about 40. miles, and the bredth from the Shire-ſtones in the Weſt to <hi>Butter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Eaſt</hi> (which is the broadeſt part of the Shire) ſpreadeth 29. miles, making the compaſſe of the whole Shire much vpon 140. miles. This County is diuided into 29. Hundreds, wherein are 304. Pariſh Churches; and it is well watered and irriguated with 5. Riuers, ouer which is conuenient paſſage by 31. Bridges. It hath beene fortified alſo with 8. Caſtles of ſtrength, viz. <hi>Malmesbury, Caſtlecombe, Lacocke, The Deuiſes, Lurgiſhall, Warder-Caſtle, Salisbury,</hi> and <hi>Marlingsborough.</hi> It is traffiqued for commerce with 21. Market Townes, the chiefe whereof is the Citie of <hi>Salisburie,</hi> which in time paſt was placed ſome what higher than it is now, but was changed to a farre fitter place, where it is plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully accommodated with pleaſant Riuerets of freſh running water, paſſing thorow many of the ſtreets. It is adorned with many beautifull buildings, hauing a moſt ſumptuous Cathedrall Church, wherein are as many doores as there are moneths, as many windowes as there are dayes, as many marble pilla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s as there be houres in the yeare. This Church was begun by <hi>Richard Poore</hi> a Biſhop, being 40. yeares before it was finiſhed: And (as my ſelfe haue read in an ancient Record yet remaining in the Treaſurie there) amongſt all the workmen that were at the building thereof, he that had the greateſt wages, had but three halfe pence a day and found himſelfe. This Citie is placed for Latitude 51. 5. and for Longitude 22. 35. Not farre from this, but ſomewhat higher, ſtands old <hi>Salisburie,</hi> which was anciently the ſeat of the <hi>Romans,</hi> but now is transformed to ruines. This County is decked with many faire edifices, and in times paſt hath had the foundations of many Monaſteries and Religious Houſes, whereof that at <hi>Malmesburie</hi> was of great note for <hi>William</hi> the Monke of <hi>Malmesburie,</hi> who with great induſtrie recorded the hiſtorie of this our Land; and another at <hi>Ambresburie,</hi> where Queene <hi>Eleanor</hi> wife to King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third ſpent her widowhood as a Nunne; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides diuers others which would be here too tedious to recite. This Shire is both pleaſant and fertile, being ſituate in a temperate clime, and moſt wholeſome. The North part (commonly called <hi>North-Wiltſhire</hi>) is both hillie and wooddie, which beſides many other delectable Riuerets, is watered with the famous Riuer <hi>Iſis.</hi> But the South being not ſo hillie, thorow which paſſe the Riuers <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly, Adder,</hi> and <hi>Alton,</hi> is inriched moſt plentifully with graſſe and corne: And the middle part, ſituate betweene them both, very leuell and euen, called <hi>Salisbury Plaines,</hi> whereon doe graze an infinite number of ſleecie ſheepe. At a little village in this County, called <hi>Calne, Ann. Dom.</hi> 977. was aſſembled a Synod about the mariages of the Clergie, where by the ſudden breaking of the floore of the roome wherein they were, very many both of the Nobles, Prelates, and Commons, were ſlaine and ſore hurt; but <hi>Dunſtan</hi> the Preſident was only vntouched.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:19"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Wiltshire</figDesc>
                     <head>WILT SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Hampshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:20"/>
               <head>Hamp-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Shire by the <hi>Saxons</hi> was called <hi>Handerchyr,</hi> hauing his North ſide butting vpon <hi>Barkſhire,</hi> his Eaſt vpon <hi>Survey, Suſſex</hi> with the Brittiſh Seas bounding his South ſide, and <hi>Dorſet</hi> and <hi>Wilt ſhires</hi> with the Ile of <hi>Wight</hi> oppoſing his Weſt. The length of this County from <hi>Baſcomb</hi> South to <hi>Bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kwater</hi> North containeth 54. Miles, &amp; the bredth from <hi>Petersfield</hi> Eaſt, to <hi>Tedworth</hi> Weſt about 29. or 30. Miles, making about 155. the whole circumference. It is diuided into 37. Hundreds, wherein are contained 253. pariſh Churches. It is watered with 4. Riuers, ouer which for paſſage are 31. Bridges, and it is commodiouſly furniſhed with faire Hauens for ſhips, as at <hi>Southampton, Portſmouth, Tich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> and <hi>Hamble,</hi> &amp;c. It is fortified with diuers ſtrong Caſtles, as at <hi>Southampton, Calſhot, Hurſt,</hi> Saint <hi>Andrewes, Porcheſter, Worth,</hi> and the South Caſtle, with diuers other places of ſtrength which are ſituate on the Sea coaſt, for defence of the County: Beſides at <hi>Wincheſter, Malwood,</hi> and <hi>Odiam,</hi> which are ſeated within Land. Marker Townes for commerce are in this Shire 18. wherof the Citie of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> is the chiefe, which by the <hi>Britans</hi> was called <hi>Caer Gwent;</hi> by the <hi>Romans, Venta Belgarum,</hi> and the <hi>Saxons Windanearder:</hi> it was built by <hi>Rudbudibras,</hi> before our Sauiours natiuitie 900. yeares, and after it had beene twice conſumed by fire in the time of the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons,</hi> was reedified, the walls raiſed, and made the chiefe ſeat of the <hi>Weſt-Saxon</hi> Kings, and the Metropolitane Sea of their Biſhops: wherein were crowned <hi>Egbert,</hi> and <hi>Elfred,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> 3. was borne. In the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> 3. this Citie was made the ſtaple for Cloth and Wooll, and in the Cathedrall Church of this Citie haue diuers Engliſh Kings beene interred. The ſituation of this City is in a bottome vnder hills, very pleaſant and fruitfull, hauing the Caſtle on the one ſide, and the Riuer on the other, the walls which ingirt it containing neare two Engliſh Miles, hauing 6. Gates for entrance, and 7. Churches within it beſides the Cathedrall; but heretofore it hath beene adorned with many others which now remaine nothing but Ruines. The graduation of this Citie for Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is 51. 5. and for Longitude 23. 10. The next to this in this Shire is the Towne of <hi>Southampton,</hi> from which the whole Shire hath the name; it is both beautifull and rich, walled with a ſtrong ſtone wall, wherein are 7. gates, and 29. Towers, and two faire Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens for ſhips, 5. Churches, and an Hoſpitall; and on the Weſt ſide of this Towne ſtandeth a fair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrong double walled Caſtle, vpon the Top of a very faire high hill, making a moſt delightfull proſpect both by Sea and Land. The aire in this Shire is very tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, though ſometimes ſomewhat foggy, which proceeds from the Seas adioyning to it, and the Riuers paſſing thorow it, which notwithſtanding doe ſtore the Countrey with plentie of fiſh. And for the ſoile it is both rich and pleaſant, producing plenty of Corne, Cattell, Woods, and Paſture, bountifully ſtoring the Inhabitants with Woolls, Cloths, Iron, and almoſt all kinde of profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table commodities, both by Sea and Land.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:20"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Hampshire</figDesc>
                     <head>HANT SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Berkshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:21"/>
               <head>Barke-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Engliſh Saxons</hi> called this Shire <hi>Berrocſcyre,</hi> which on the North is diuided from <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Oxford</hi>-ſhires by the Riuer of <hi>Thames,</hi> on the South it butteth on <hi>Hamp-ſhire,</hi> the Eaſt is bounded with <hi>Surrey,</hi> and the Weſt with <hi>Wilt-ſhire</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire.</hi> The length from <hi>Ingleſham</hi> Weſt, to old <hi>Windſor</hi> in the Eaſt, being about 40. Miles, and the bredth from <hi>Inkpen</hi> South, to <hi>Wightham</hi> North, 24. Miles, maketh the compaſſe much vpon 120. Miles. This County is parted in 20. Hundreds, which containe in them 140. Pariſh Churches. It is interlaced with 3. Riuers, which for conuenient paſſage haue 7. Bridges. 13. Market Townes are alſo diſperſed in it for the commoditie &amp; commerce of the Inhabitants, whereof <hi>Reading</hi> is the chiefe, where the <hi>Danes An.</hi> 866. ſetled and fortified themſelues. But it was built by King <hi>Henry</hi> 1. who adorned it both with a faire Monaſterie and ſtrong Caſtle, which the firſt <hi>Henry</hi> raiſed, and the 2. <hi>Henry</hi> razed and turned to Ruines. The Latitude here is 51. 31. degrees, and Longitude 23. 34 In this Shire is ſeated that famous and ſtately Caſtle of <hi>Windſor,</hi> which ſometimes did belong to the Abbot of <hi>Weſtm.</hi> till <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour by compoſition obtained it, and made it his Regall Palace. In it was borne King <hi>Edward</hi> 3 who afterwards held there (as his priſoners) <hi>Iohn</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> King of <hi>Scots.</hi> In this Caſtle is alſo celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the famous and memorable inſtitution of that moſt honourable order of the Garter, and in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell thereof lie interred the bodies of K. <hi>Henry</hi> 6. <hi>Edward</hi> 4. and <hi>Henry</hi> 8. <hi>Wallingford, Watham</hi> in the Eaſt, and <hi>Sinodum</hi> in the North, in this Shire were all places of reſidence for the <hi>Romans,</hi> as appeareth by their moneys which very often are found in thoſe places. And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Stow</hi> writeth, that at <hi>Finchamſted</hi> in the yeare of grace 1100. did a wonderfull ſpring boyle vp for the ſpace of 15. dayes ſending forth ſtreames of bloud. This County is adorned with many faire and ſtately buildings, 6. faire Caſtles, 3. of his Maieſties houſes, and in times paſt had diuers Religious houſes and Monaſteries, at <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>gton, Reading, Byſham, Bromhall, Hernly, Hamme,</hi> and <hi>Wallingford.</hi> The aire is pleaſant, temperate, and wholſome, the ſoyle bringing plenty of Corne and paſturage, yeelding an abundance of increaſe, eſpecially in the Vale of <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ehorſe.</hi> But generally the whole County both for profit and pleaſure (producing Corne and Cattell, with woods, waters, and very delightfull proſpects) is inferiour for the quantitie to no other Shire in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:21"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Berkshire</figDesc>
                     <head>BARKE SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Surrey" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:22"/>
               <head>Surrey.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vrrey</hi> was called by the <hi>Saxons Suthrea,</hi> and by <hi>Beda Suthri.</hi> It is bounded on the North with the Counties of <hi>Buckingham</hi> and <hi>Middleſex,</hi> and diuided from them by the River of <hi>Thames: Suſſex</hi> and <hi>Hampſhire</hi> incloſe it on the South, <hi>Kent</hi> on the Eaſt, and <hi>Hampſhire</hi> and <hi>Barkſhire</hi> on the Weſt. This Shire is as it were ſquare in forme; yet the length (extending from <hi>Frenſham</hi> to <hi>Redrith</hi>) containeth 34. miles, and the bredth (from <hi>Aufold</hi> Southward to the <hi>Thames</hi> by <hi>Stanes</hi> Northward) is 22. miles, which makes the Shires circuit about 112. miles. It is diuided into 13. Hundreds, which containe in them 140. Pariſh Churches, and 8. Market Townes for traffique and commerce. In this County is no Citie nor great Towne, and yet may it compare with any for faire buildings and ſtately houſes, whereof 5. are his Maieſties magnificent Palaces. <hi>Ptolemy</hi> affirmeth, that in this County an ancient people called the <hi>Regni</hi> had their reſidence, and after that <hi>Ella</hi> with the <hi>South-Saxons</hi> made it their Kingdome. At <hi>Lambeth</hi> (which was founded by Archbiſhop <hi>Baldwin,</hi> and is now a Palace for the Archbiſhops of <hi>Canterburie,</hi> and famous for being the ſeat of the Metropolitans of <hi>England) Canutus</hi> died, who was the laſt King of the <hi>Danes.</hi> And at <hi>Kingston</hi> in this County were crowned King <hi>Athelſtan, Edwin,</hi> and <hi>Ethelred.</hi> And at the ancient Towne of <hi>Guildford</hi> (whoſe Pole for Latitude is eleuated 51. 15. and Longitude 24.59.) was ſeated the royall Palace of the <hi>Engliſh-Saxon</hi> Kings. This Shire hath beene adorned with the foundations of many faire and rich Religious Houſes, as at <hi>Shene, Chertſey, Newarke, Rigate, Merton, Wauerley,</hi> and diuers others: And alſo 8. ſtrong Caſtles, at <hi>Brenchingley, Goſeford, Guilford, Farnham, Rigate, Darking, Starburg,</hi> and <hi>Addington:</hi> but of moſt of them is nought now to be ſeene, but heaps of old ruines. This County is ſeated in a very delectable, pleaſant, and wholeſome aire; and though it be not large, and altogether ſo commodious as others for profit, yet is it pleaſurable and healthie, yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſufficient ſtore of corne, fruit, and paſture.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:22"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Surrey</figDesc>
                     <head>SURREY</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Middlesex" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:23"/>
               <head>Middleſex.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His County was ſo called for being ſeated betweene the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Saxons</hi> and is bounded on the Eaſt by the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Lea,</hi> where it butteth vpon <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and on the Weſt by <hi>Colne</hi> is diuided from <hi>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kingham.</hi> The <hi>Thames</hi> parts <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rey</hi> from it on the South, and <hi>Hartford-ſhire</hi> incloſeth it on the North. The length from <hi>Stratford</hi> in the Eaſt to <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ehall</hi> in the Weſt, containes of our Engliſh Miles 19. and the bredth from <hi>Hampton Court</hi> South to <hi>South-Mines</hi> in the North about 16. meaſuring the whole circumference about 90. Miles. It is diſtinguiſhed into theſe 7. Hundreds, viz. <hi>Edmonton, Oſulſlon, Finnesbury, G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re. Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eworth, Spelthorne,</hi> and <hi>Elthorne,</hi> in all which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained 73. Pariſh Churches beſides thoſe in <hi>London.</hi> This County (though ſmaller in quantitie than many other) is the chiefeſt of all the Land both for beauty and ability, wherein are 2. Cities, and is watered with the moſt famous Riuer of <hi>Thames,</hi> being plentifully ſtored with Ships of great burthen, which continually ſend out and bring in all manner of wealthy commodities, for the abundant enriching of all theſe his Maieſties Dominions; which Riuer carries her courſe all along the South ſide of the farre renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and euer famous Citie of <hi>London,</hi> which for antiquity hath almoſt worne out her Records; yet we reade ſhe was firſt called <hi>Troy-Nouant,</hi> from <hi>Bru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> and <hi>Ludſtone</hi> from King <hi>Lud,</hi> by the <hi>Britans Londaine,</hi> by the <hi>Saxons London Cearder,</hi> and now by vs <hi>London.</hi> It is the rich Seat and Royall Chamber of the Engliſh Kings, whereto from all parts of the world are brought all ſorts of commodious Merchandize. Shee was firſt compaſſed with walls by the firſt Chriſtian Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, wherein beſides other paſſages, are now built 7. moſt Magnificent Gates for entrance, and in it with the Suburbs are contained 121. Churches, beſides the Cathedrall of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> which (as by tradition is receiued) was firſt the Temple of <hi>Diana.</hi> This Cities graduation is 51. 32½. of Latitude, and in Longitude 24. 27. It is diuided into 26. wards, which by a Lord Maior, two Sherifes, and 26. Aldermen, is moſt religiouſly in all good order gouerned. In the time of King <hi>Iohn</hi> was the ſtone Bridge built ouer the <hi>Thames,</hi> which for ſtrength, length, bredth, and beauty, exceeds all others in the world. Cloſe adioyning to this <hi>London</hi> is the Citie of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> famous as well for the ſeats of Iuſtice, as for the rich and ſtately Sepulchers of many Kings, Queenes, and other the Nobilitie of England. But if I ſhould inſiſt any longer in the particular deſcriptions of theſe Cities, I ſhould exceed my limits, and therefore generally for the County thus. It is adorned with very many rich and magnificent edifices, whereof 5. are his Maieſties princely Palaces. The forme of this Shire is ſquare-like: The Aire delightfull, pleaſant and healthfull, and the Soile rich and fruitfull, yeelding great plenty of full Corne of all kindes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fat Paſture in abundance.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:23"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Middlesex</figDesc>
                     <head>MIDDLESSEX</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Kent" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:24"/>
               <head>Kent.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His County of <hi>Kent,</hi> which by <hi>Ptolemy</hi> and diuers other Writers was called <hi>Cantium,</hi> is boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the Eaſt with the Germane Sea, on the Weſt with <hi>Suſſex</hi> and <hi>Surrey,</hi> on the North with the Riuer of <hi>Thames,</hi> and on the South with the narrow Seas and <hi>Suſſex.</hi> It runneth in length from <hi>Langley</hi> Weſt to <hi>Ramſgate</hi> Eaſt, about 53. Miles, &amp; from <hi>Rother</hi> South vnto the Northern Iſle of <hi>Graine,</hi> about 26. Miles, whereby the whole circuit containeth much vpon 160. Miles. It is diuided into 5. Lathes, and they into 66. Hundreds, wherein are counted 398. Pariſh Churches. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of it is watered with 11. faire Riuers, ouer which is paſſage by 14. Bridges, and diuers of them are nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, whereof <hi>Medwey</hi> which diuideth the Shire in two parts is principall. It is fortified with 27. Caſtles, and hath in it 2. Cities, 2. Biſhops Seas, and for commerce and traffique 24. Market Townes; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing beſides gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and fairely adorned with diuers ſtately and ſumptuous buildings, whereof 8. of them are his Maieſties Houſes. The chiefeſt Citie is <hi>Canterbury,</hi> which is the Metrapolitan and Archbiſhops Sea. It was built 900. yeares before the birth of our Sauiour, (as we read in the ancient Brittiſh Hiſtories) but afterwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d it became moſt famous by <hi>Auſten</hi> the Monke, his conuerting the <hi>Saxons</hi> to Chriſtianity, and for the Cathedrall Church wherein is the Tombe of <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Becket,</hi> which in the time of Idolatrie became infinitely rich by ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious offerings. In it was King <hi>Iohn</hi> with Queene <hi>Iſabel</hi> his wife crowned, King <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. maried, and <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. buried. <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. granted it afterwards priuiledges and Charters <hi>Richard</hi> the 2. fortified and entrenched it, and Archbiſhop <hi>Sudbury</hi> walled it. The graduation for Latitude being there 50. 18. and the Longitude 25. 41. This Shire is well ſtored with faire Hauens for ſhips, ſome of them being ſtrongly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, as <hi>Winchelſey, Rumney, Sandwich,</hi> and <hi>Douer,</hi> which with the Caſtle there is accounted the Locke and Key of the Realme. The Inhabitants of this County doe account themſelues the freeſt of any other in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> becauſe they were neuer conquered, but by Conquering <hi>Willi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m</hi> were compounded withall. The Chriſtian faith was firſt planted in this County, and (as ancient Records doe teſtifie) the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Church dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſeruice of Chriſt was founded in <hi>Douer</hi> Caſtle by <hi>Lucius</hi> the firſt Chriſtian King of the <hi>Brittaines.</hi> In this Shire haue beene ſeated 23. Religious Houſes, which now by time are conuerted to Ruines. The Aire of this County is temperate and healthfull, though ſometimes miſt-clouded with vapours from the Sea. The Eaſt ſide of the Shire is Hilly, but the Weſt more plaine, euen, &amp; wooddy, yeelding generally great ſtore of all profitable commodities, but is moſt remarkable for Broad cloths, fruits, and feedings for Cattell.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:24"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Kent</figDesc>
                     <head>KENT</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Sussex" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:25"/>
               <head>Suſſex.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Shire which of vs is called <hi>Suſſex,</hi> was written by the <hi>Saxons Suthrex,</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnifying as if it were their South King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in the time of their Heptarchie. It is confined on the North with <hi>Surrey</hi> and <hi>Kent,</hi> on the Weſt with <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> the Brittiſh Seas ingirting both the Eaſt and South. It is formed long and narrow, ſtretching in length from <hi>Weſt-harting</hi> in the Weſt to the Ditch that diuides it from <hi>Kent,</hi> called <hi>Kent</hi> Ditch, 64. Miles, but where it is broadeſt it containes not aboue 20. making the compaſſe of it about 158. Miles. This Shire diuideth it ſelfe into 6 <hi>Rapes,</hi> viz. <hi>Chicheſter, Arundell, Bramber, Lewes, Peuenſcy,</hi> and <hi>Haſtings;</hi> and euery of theſe haue ſeuerall Hundreds, an cunting in all to the number of 65. which containe in them 312. Pariſh Churches. Induſtrious M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Speed</hi> alſo writes that euery of theſe <hi>Rapes</hi> containe in them a Riuer, a Caſtle, and a Foreſt. The ancient Inhabitants of this County were the <hi>Regni</hi> in time of the <hi>Romans,</hi> who were ſubdued by the Lieutenant of the Emperour <hi>Claudius,</hi> and after the <hi>Romans</hi> departure, this Shire and <hi>Surrey</hi> became the Kingdome of the <hi>South-Saxons.</hi> Diuers places of note are regiſtred in this County, but the chiefeſt of all is the City of <hi>Chicheſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er,</hi> which by the <hi>Saxons</hi> was written <hi>Ciſſan-Ceaſder,</hi> built by <hi>Ciſſa</hi> the <hi>South-Saxon</hi> King, who therein kept his Court. It is large, faire, and well fortified with a wall, and was made the Biſhops Sea by <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour. The Pole being there eleuated 50. 52. and hath Longitude 23. 50. This Shire hath beene both ſtrengthened and beautified with 10. Caſtles, and many Religious Houſes, which were built for pious uſes, but are now diſſolued into Ruines. 18. Market-Townes for tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffique of the Inhabitants are fitly ſeated in this County, whereof <hi>Chicheſter</hi> formerly ſpoken of is the chiefe, although <hi>Lewes</hi> both for bigneſſe and faire buildings ſeemeth to compare with it. The aire in this Shire is both temperate and pleaſant, though ſometimes darkned with miſts ariſing from the Seas. The Soyle is rich, yeelding great plentie of neceſſary commodities, though in Winter it is both vnpleaſant and vnſafe for Trauellers by reaſon of the deepe and dangerous wayes in it. It yeeldeth great plenty of Fiſh and Sea-Fowle, with Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, Cattell, and Woods; and ſo doth it of Iron and Glaſſe good ſtore, which are the two deuourers of thoſe faire Woods. The middeſt of this Shire is decked with many faire Meadowes, Paſtures, and Corne fields. But towards the Sea ſide are ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted diuers Hills called the Downes, which produce abundance of Corne and Graſſe: The reſt of the Shire being yet ſtored with plenty of pleaſant Groues and Woods.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:25"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Sussex</figDesc>
                     <head>SUSSEX</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Essex" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:26"/>
               <head>Eſſex.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His County (which by the <hi>Saxons</hi> was called <hi>Eaſt-ſeaxa,</hi> by the <hi>Normans Exſſeſa,</hi> &amp; now by vs <hi>Eſſex</hi>) containes in length from <hi>Horſey Iſland</hi> Eaſt to <hi>Haydon</hi> Weſt 40. Miles, and from <hi>Stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere</hi> on the Riuer <hi>Stow</hi> North to <hi>Eaſt-ham</hi> vpon <hi>Thames</hi> South 35. Miles, making the forme ſomewhat circular, and the circumference to beare about 146. Miles. It is confined on the Eaſt with the Germane Seas, on the Weſt with <hi>Hertfordſhire</hi> and <hi>Middleſex.</hi> The <hi>Thames</hi> diuides it from <hi>Kent</hi> on the South, and <hi>Suffolke</hi> and <hi>Cambridgſhires</hi> bind it on the North. The diuiſion of it is into 20. Hundreds, which containe in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 415. Pariſh Churches. It hath 7. Riuers, ouer w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is paſſage by 28. Bridges: and for delight is furniſhed with 46. Parkes &amp; one Chaſe well ſtored with game. The Inhabitants here haue intercourſe for traffique and commerce in 21. Market Townes, the chiefeſt wherof is now the City of <hi>Colche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> which was built by the Brittiſh Prince <hi>Coilus, Ann. Dom.</hi> 124. and in it was borne <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the firſt Chriſtian King and Emperour in the world. It is ſeated on the South ſide of the Riuer <hi>Colne,</hi> &amp; therof beares the name. It hath beene fortified with a wall, wherein are 6. Gates, beſides 3. ſmaller Poſterns for paſſage, and 9. Towers, &amp; within and without the walls hath it 10. faire Churches, beſides diuers other foundations of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Houſes, which are now vtterly decaied as well as the old Caſtle, which by the Ruines appeares in times paſt to haue beene of very great ſtrength. This Citie is gouerned by 2. Bailiffes, 12. Aldermen, and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder. The Latitude being there 51. 52. and the Longitude 25. 37. In the ancient Towne of <hi>Malden</hi> in this County <hi>Cuno-belin</hi> that was King of the <hi>Trinobants,</hi> held his Court about the time of our Sauiours birth, and was afterwards a gariſon for the <hi>Romans,</hi> till Queene <hi>Budo</hi> with the ſlaughter of 70000. <hi>Romans</hi> laid it leuell with the foundation. This County is very populous, and hath beene beautified with many faire and rich Religious Houſes, and ſtrengthened with 5. ſtrong Caſtles. It is accommodated alſo with 5. conuenient Hauens for ſhips. The Aire (except by the Sea ſide) is both temperate and pleaſant, the Soile moſt fertile, yeelding very many excellent commodities, as Corne, Cattell, Woods, Fiſh, Fowle, and that rich merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of the beſt Saffron, which where it groweth ſo fatneth the ground, that after three yeares gleabe thereof, the land for 18. yeares after brings forth Barly in abundance. Here are alſo many faire flocks of fine fleeced ſheepe, which in this County they vſe to milke as they doe their Kine, whereby is made much cheeſe, which (beſides the furniſhing of their owne Country) is tranſported and vttered in diuers other parts abroad.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:26"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Essex</figDesc>
                     <head>THE COVNTY OF ESSEX.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Hertfordshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:27"/>
               <head>Hartford-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ford-ſhir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (ſo called from the Shire-Towne <hi>Hartford,</hi> which ſome haue named <hi>Herudford</hi>) is of a circular forme, making 2. Diameters almoſt of an equall Longitude, croſſe each other in the Center; for the one giuing the length from <hi>Cheſton Nunnery</hi> in the Eaſt to <hi>Putnam</hi> Weſt containes but 28. miles, and the other North &amp; South, meaſuring the bredth from <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſton</hi> to <hi>Totteridge,</hi> is full 27. making the whole circumference to containe neare about 130. Miles. It is bounded on the Eaſt ſide by <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and on the Weſt with <hi>Buckingham</hi> and <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford-ſhires;</hi> the North butteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon <hi>Bedford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge-ſhires,</hi> and the South vpon <hi>Middleſex.</hi> This Shire is watered but with one Riuer, yet hath it many Riuerets, and 24. Bridges, and 120 Pariſh-Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are contained in theſe 8. Hundreds, <hi>Odſey, Edwinſtree, Branghing, Brodewater, Hitching, Dacor, Hert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> and <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſho,</hi> whereinto this Shire is diuided. And it is traded for the vtterance of commodities, and traffique amongſt the Inhabitants, with 18 Market Townes, whereof though <hi>Hartford</hi> be the Shire-Towne, and hath gotten her Officer in chiefe to be altered from a Burgeſſe to a Maior, (who aſſociated with nine Burgeſſes and a Recorder doth gouerne it) yet is <hi>Ware</hi> and others for abilitie the better, by reaſon of the continuall paſſage of people, that make therein their thorow-fare almoſt into all the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne parts of this Realme. Here in this Towne was ſometime ſeated a faire and ſtrong Caſtle, which now appeares to haue taſted the ſcourge of Time, as well as diuers other famous and richly endowed Relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous Houſes that in former times haue gorgeouſly adorned this County. The Longitude is here 24. 25. and the Latitude 51. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Neere to <hi>Saint Albans</hi> (that ancient Towne, made famous for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Battels there fought) in this Shire was ſeated that ſtrong and magnificent Citie of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erulam,</hi> which was ouercome by the <hi>Romans,</hi> and endowed with the priuileges of <hi>Rome,</hi> but now lies dead and buried vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the heaps of her owne ruines. The aire in this County is temperate, delightfull, and healthfull; the ſoile commodious, rich, and fruitfull, plentifully producing ſtore of Cattell, Corne, Graſſe, and Wood, with diuers other commodities moſt vſefull for the Inhabitants.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:27"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Hertfordshire</figDesc>
                     <head>HARTFORD SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Buckinghamshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:28"/>
               <head>Buckingham-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Shire is ſuppoſed to deriue the name from the <hi>Saxon</hi> word <hi>Bucken,</hi> which in that lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage ſignifieth <hi>Beech-trees,</hi> whereof this County is plentifully ſtored. It reacheth in length (from <hi>Bradfield</hi> in the North to <hi>Waisburie</hi> the furtheſt part South) 39. miles, and the bredth (from <hi>Aſhridge</hi> Eaſt to the Foreſt of <hi>Brenwood</hi> Weſt) 18. miles, whereby the whole circuit is about 138 miles. The bounds of this Shire are <hi>Northampton</hi> and <hi>Bedford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhires</hi> on the North, part of <hi>Bedford</hi> and <hi>Hertford-ſhires</hi> on the Eaſt, <hi>Barkeſhire</hi> on the South, and <hi>Oxford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> on the Weſt. This Prouince is parted into 8 Hundreds, which are furniſhed with 185 Pariſh-Churches. It is watered with two Riuers, which haue 14 Bridges for paſſage: And for conuenient traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique of their commodities, it is interſperſed with 11 Market Townes, whereof the chiefe is <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> the Shire-Towne, which is ſituated vpon the Riuer <hi>Ouſe,</hi> which compaſſeth the Towne on all ſides but the North. In times paſt it hath beene fortified by King <hi>Edward</hi> the elder with Sconces on both ſides of the Riuer, ouer which are built three faire ſtone Bridges: and vpon a high hill in the middeſt of the Towne was ſometime raiſed a ſtrong Caſtle, which is now vtterly raſed to duſtie ruines. A Bailiffe with 12 Burgeſſes doe now very orderly gouerne this Towne, where the eleuation of the Pole is 52. 2. and the Longitude 23. 30. At <hi>Stony Stretford</hi> an ancient Towne in this Shire, ſtanding vpon the Cauſey called <hi>Watling-ſtreet,</hi> which paſſeth thorow <hi>England,</hi> is a Croſſe, built by King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt for a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of <hi>Eleanor</hi> his Queene, becauſe there her dead corps reſted, as it was brought from <hi>Herdby</hi> in <hi>Lincolne-ſhire,</hi> to be buried at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> and the like did he doe in euery place where it reſted. This Shire hath beene ſtrengthned with 4 Caſtles, <hi>viz.</hi> at <hi>Buckingham, Newport, Launden,</hi> and <hi>Hampſleepe,</hi> and was alſo beautified with many Religious Houſes, which time hath now ruined, and conuerted to other vſes. The Aire in this County is temperate, wholeſome, and pleaſant; and the Soile (by reaſon of his fatneſſe) is both rich and fruitfull, yeelding Corne, Graſſe, and Marle in abundance. The middle part of the Shire being high, called the <hi>Chilterne Hills,</hi> hath beene and ſtill is well ſtored with woods; and the Vallies lying plaine, are very fruitfull for medowes, tillage, and paſtures, feeding infinite numbers of fleecie ſheepe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:28"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Buckinghamshire</figDesc>
                     <head>BVCKINGHAM SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Oxfordshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:29"/>
               <head>Oxford-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Hiſtories of our <hi>Engliſh-Saxons</hi> ſay, that the Citie of <hi>Oxford</hi> deriueth the name from the Foord of <hi>Oxen,</hi> from which Citie the whole County is called <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> which is enuironed on the North ſide with <hi>Warwicke</hi> and <hi>Northampton-ſhires,</hi> on the Eaſt with <hi>Buckingham,</hi> the Weſt with <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> and the South by <hi>Barkſhire.</hi> It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth in length, from <hi>Cleydon</hi> North-weſt to <hi>Cauerſham</hi> South-eaſt, neere forty miles; and in bredth, from the aforeſaid <hi>Cleydon</hi> North to <hi>Farringdon</hi> vpon the Riuer <hi>Iſis</hi> in the South (which is the broadeſt of the Shire) almoſt 26. miles, cauſing the circumference to come neere to 130 miles. This County is diuided into 14 Hundreds, and they haue 280 Pariſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches contained in them. It is interlaced with 3. Riuers, which are fitted with 26. Bridges. Foure Foreſts and 9 Parks doe alſo beautifie this County; and for commerce and traffique of commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities there are diſperſed 10 Market Townes, the chiefe whereof is the faire Citie and euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Vniuerſitie of <hi>Oxford,</hi> which for the infinite numbers of moſt learned, reuerend, and famous Fathers, Doctors &amp; Scholers it hath produced, and enriched this Kingdome withal, hath made it ſelfe not only glorious in this our Nation, but purchaſed an euer-liuing fame and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie thorow all the Kingdomes of Chriſtendome. This Citie hath beene walled, and ſtrongly fortified with a Caſtle, which though time hath now vtterly ruined, yet is it adorned with 17 moſt ſtately Colleges, 8 Halls, and many other moſt beautifull buildings. The Pole is there ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated 51. 47. and the Longitude 23. 15. About ſix miles from this Citie is ſeated <hi>Woodflocke,</hi> where King <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. built a Labyrinth to keepe his faire Concubine <hi>Roſamond,</hi> who was afterward poiſoned by the Queene, and buried in the Nunnery at <hi>Godſtow</hi> neere thereto adioyning. This County is adorned with many faire Mannors and beautifull buildings, wherein (as by their ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines doth appeare) haue beene many ſtately and richly endowed Religious Houſes, as <hi>Oſeney, Godſtow, Tame, Burcheſter, Euiſham, Beuerne,</hi> and diuers others. The Aire in this County is both ſweet, pleaſant, and healthfull; The Soile rich, commodious, and fruitfull, yeelding to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants great plenty of Wood, Wooll, Cattell, Corne, Paſture, and (in a word) almoſt all vſefull commodities in abundance.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:29"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Oxfordshire</figDesc>
                     <head>OXFORD SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Gloucestershire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:30"/>
               <head>Gloceſter-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Loceſterſhire</hi> in the <hi>Saxon</hi> tongue was called <hi>Gleauceſderſchyre,</hi> fetching the name from the chiefeſt Towne the Citie of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi> It is ingirt with <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>Warwickeſhires</hi> on the North, <hi>Somerſetſhire</hi> on the South, <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Wiltſhires</hi> on the Eaſt, and <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>refordſhire</hi> on the Weſt. The length of it (reaching from <hi>Briſtow</hi> vpon <hi>Auon</hi> South, to <hi>Clifford</hi> vpon <hi>Auon</hi> North) is much vpon 48 miles; and the bredth (extending from <hi>Lechlad</hi> Eaſt to <hi>Preſton</hi> Weſt) 28. which cauſeth the whole compaſſe to containe about 138 miles. The ancient Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of this County were the <hi>Dobuni,</hi> and in ſome part the <hi>Silures.</hi> This Prouince is diuided into 30 Hundreds, which containe in them 280 Pariſh-Churches. It hath three faire Riuers, ouer which a man may paſſe by 22 Bridges; the chiefe whereof is <hi>Seuerne,</hi> which for ſtore of Fiſh, bredth of Channell, and ſwiftneſſe of Streame, excelleth any other in the Land. It is conueniently ſprinkled with 25 Market-Townes for trade and traffique, whereof two are famous Cities, whereof the firſt and moſt ancient is <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> which about the middle of the Shire is ſituate vpon the Riuer <hi>Seuerne.</hi> It was built by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and was the Garriſon Towne for their <hi>Colonia Gleuum,</hi> It hath beene ſtrongly walled on all parts but that towards the Riuer, as may appeare by the ruines yet remaining in many places. There was the ſtately Nunnerie built by <hi>Oſrick</hi> King of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> wherein three of the <hi>Mercian</hi> Queenes ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one another, being Prioreſſes. The Cathedrall Church (firſt built by <hi>Edelſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed,</hi> King <hi>Edward</hi> the elders ſiſter) was ruinated by the <hi>Danes,</hi> but afterwards reedified, and dedicated to <hi>S. Peter,</hi> where King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, who was murdered at <hi>Barkley</hi> Caſtle, lies intombed. The Graduation of the Pole in this Citie is 51. 54. and Longitude 22. 17. The other Citie, which ſtandeth but part in this Shire, and part in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> is <hi>Briſtow,</hi> ſeated vpon the two Riuers <hi>Froome</hi> and <hi>Auon,</hi> and, as is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſaid, (the quantitie excepted) for qualitie is parallel to the chiefeſt in <hi>England.</hi> In the Iland <hi>Alney</hi> neere <hi>Gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceſter, Edmund Iron-ſide</hi> combatted hand to hand with <hi>Canutus</hi> the <hi>Dane:</hi> And at <hi>Barkley</hi> Caſtle King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond had a red hot ſpit thruſt thorow his fundament into his belly. The foundations of many Religious Houſes haue beene both raiſed vp, and raſed downe in this County, where the Aire is very pleaſant and delectable, the Soile being ſo fruitfull by nature, that the very Hedge-rowes of their owne accord bring plenty of excellent fruits, and in times paſt hath yeelded abundance of moſt pleaſant Vines; but now it produceth ſtore of Corne, Fruits, F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne Wools, and Iron, and is moſt pleaſantly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated with Woods and Paſture.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:30"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Gloucestershire</figDesc>
                     <head>GLOCESTER SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Worcestershire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:31"/>
               <head>Worceſter-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the <hi>Engliſh Saxons</hi> this County was written <hi>Wirceaſderſcyre,</hi> which wee call <hi>Worceſter ſhire,</hi> which being inuerged on the Eaſt with <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Warwicke-ſhires,</hi> is on the Weſt diuided from <hi>Herefordſhire</hi> by <hi>Maluerne</hi> Hills: the South is inuironed with <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire,</hi> and the North with the County of <hi>Stafford.</hi> It reacheth in length (from <hi>Ridmerly</hi> South to <hi>Yardley</hi> North) 32 miles, and the bredth (from <hi>Church Honyborne</hi> Eaſt to <hi>Tenbury</hi> Weſt) about 28. which maketh the whole circumference to amount much vpon 120 miles. Into 7 Hundreds is this Shire diuided, and thoſe containe in them 152 Pariſh-Churches. It hath but one Citie, one Biſhopricke, but is pleaſantly watered with foure faire Riuers, as <hi>Auon, Tame, Salwarpe,</hi> and <hi>Seuerne,</hi> which paſſeth almoſt thorow the Center of the Shire: and theſe may be paſſed ouer by 13 Bridges. This Shire alſo is delighted with one Chaſe, two Foreſts, and 16 Parkes; and for concourſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce is fitted with 10 Market Townes, whereof the Citie of <hi>Worceſter</hi> (whence the County is ſo called) is the chiefeſt, which is a faire, rich, and populous Citie, moſt delightfully ſituate on the Eaſt ſide of <hi>Seuerne,</hi> being built ſomewhat like the whole Shire, in a triangular forme. The old <hi>Saxons</hi> called it <hi>Wireceaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er,</hi> the <hi>Latines Vigornia,</hi> and we <hi>Worceſter.</hi> It was founded (as is ſuppoſed) by the <hi>Romans,</hi> to oppoſt the <hi>Britaines</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is compaſſed with a wall, which giues entrance thorow ſeuen gates, and both for defence and ornament hath fiue Turrets. This Citie hath diuers times taſted of diuers fortunes, hauing beene ſometimes almoſt quite conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by fire, and otherwiſe grieuouſly oppreſſed by enemies, and yet is now againe become a famous and magnificent Citie, which hath a faire Cathedrall Church, firſt founded by <hi>Sexwolfe</hi> the Biſhop, in the yeere 680. wherein are interred the bodies of King <hi>Iohn</hi> that was poiſoned by a Monke, and Prince <hi>Arthur,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seuenths eldeſt ſonne. The gouernment of this Citie is orderly menaged by two Bailiffes, two Aldermen, two Chamberlaines, and two Conſtables, which being choſen out of 24 Burgeſſes, are annually changed. The Pole is here eleuated 52. 19. and the Longitude is 22. 17. The ancient Inhabitants of this County were the <hi>Cornauij,</hi> who in <hi>Claudius Caeſars</hi> time were ouercome by the <hi>Romans,</hi> after whoſe departure it became part of the <hi>Mercian Saxon</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>Vpton</hi> in this Shire in the <hi>Romans</hi> time was a place of Garriſon for their Legions, and to this day are many of their moneyes found there. In this County haue many famous Religious Houſes beene founded, but by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth were they raſed downe like the reſt, and nothing now remaining for their memoriall, but huge heaps of pitifull ruines. And with diuers ſtrong Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles alſo hath this County beene fortified, whereof the moſt of them haue felt the heauy hand of fortune, to ſuppreſſe them as low as their foundations were laid. In a moſt temperate and pleaſant aire is this Shire ſeated, and for fertilitie of Soile may be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted comparable to the beſt in the Land. It is plentifully ſtored with all kinde of moſt neceſſary commodities, yeelding abundance of Corne, Cattell, Woods, and Paſtures; hauing the fields and hedges ſet full of Peare trees, wherewith they make much Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y. Beſides all which, in this Prouince are many Salt Springs, and diuers other profitable commodities, which yeeld welcome gaine to the Inhabitants.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:31"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Worcestershire</figDesc>
                     <head>WORCESTER SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Warwickshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:32"/>
               <head>Warwicke-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Arwicke-ſhire</hi> is ſo called from the Shire-Towne, now vulgarly named <hi>Warwicke,</hi> but was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>armed by the <hi>Saxons Warringwicke,</hi> as our euer famous Hiſtorian <hi>M. Camden</hi> records, which he alſo iudgeth to haue beene the <hi>Romans</hi> Garriſons Towne. By <hi>Ptolemy</hi> they were called the <hi>Cornauij,</hi> wherein after were ſeated the <hi>Mercian Saxons.</hi> It is enuironed with the County of <hi>Stafford</hi> on the North, <hi>Watling-ſtreet</hi> and <hi>Northampton-ſhire</hi> on the Eaſt, <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter-ſhires</hi> on the South, and <hi>Worceſter-ſhire</hi> on the Weſt. It is extended from <hi>Newton</hi> in the North to <hi>Long Compton</hi> in the South, 33. miles, and is ſpread in wideneſſe from <hi>Hewell Grange</hi> in the Weſt to <hi>Hill Morton</hi> in the Eaſt, 25 miles, the whole circuit thereof being 135 miles. It is diuided into fiue Hundreds, viz. <hi>Hemling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, Couentry, Knightlow, Barklichway,</hi> and <hi>Kington,</hi> wherein are 158 Pariſh-Churches. This Shire is interlaced with eight Riuers, as <hi>Auon, Anker, Blyth, Bourne, Leame, Sherburne, Sowe,</hi> and <hi>Tame,</hi> being fitted with 29 Bridges. It is traded with 16 Market Townes, the chiefe whereof are <hi>Couentry</hi> and <hi>Warwicke, Couentry</hi> being ſtately adorned with faire buildings, well fortified with a Wall, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are 13 Gates, and 18 Towers, by the grant of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, whereby alſo they might elect a Maior and two Bailiffes; but by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth it was incorporated a County of it ſelfe, and the names of Bailiffes turned into Sheriffes, by which at this day it is gouerned. At <hi>Goffard</hi> Gate in the Eaſt end of this Citie, hangs the ſhield-bone of a wilde Boare, ſlaine by Sir <hi>Guy</hi> of <hi>Warwicke,</hi> as the report goes. <hi>Warwicke</hi> is built vpon the North-Eaſt banke of <hi>Auon,</hi> by <hi>Gurguſtius</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Belinus,</hi> 375 yeeres before the birth of our Sauiour. There is a very ſumptuous Caſtle lately repaired by Sir <hi>Fulke Greuill;</hi> and from the Towne ouer the Riuer is a very faire ſtrong ſtone Bridge, the paſſage into the Towne being hewed out of the Rocke. It hath two faire Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and is gouerned by a Bailiffe, 12 Brethren, and 24 Burgeſſes. This Shire is beautified with many faire Edifices, hauing had ſometime 12 notable foundations of Religious Houſes and Monaſteries, 20 Parks, and one Chaſe. The Riuer <hi>Auon</hi> hath on the North ſide the <hi>Woodland,</hi> and on the South ſide the <hi>Feilden,</hi> with the Vale of <hi>Red-Horſe.</hi> It is abundantly fruitfull, producing plenty of Corne, Wools, and Wood, with Mines of Iron and Cole. At a place called <hi>Shugborow</hi> in this Shire is found the pretious ſtone <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtorices.</hi> At <hi>Offchurch</hi> is the Palace of the great <hi>Norman</hi> Commander <hi>Offa.</hi> At <hi>Lemington</hi> (farre from the Sea) is a Spring where Salt water continually boyles vp. And at <hi>Newnham Regis</hi> is found a Well, the water whereof is very medicinable for many diſeaſes, and turneth wood into ſtone. At <hi>Guyes</hi> Cliffe neere <hi>Warwicke</hi> the famous Earle <hi>Guy</hi> (after many worthy exploits atchieued) lead an Hermites life vnknowne.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:32"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Warwickshire</figDesc>
                     <head>WARWICK SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Northamptonshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:33"/>
               <head>Northampton-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Shire, by the <hi>Saxons</hi> tearmed <hi>Northafendonſcire,</hi> and by vs <hi>Northampton-ſhire,</hi> is long and narrow, ſeated very neere the Center of <hi>England,</hi> and is bounded on the Eaſt by <hi>Huntington-ſhire,</hi> hauing the Riuer <hi>Nene</hi> to diuide them; on the Weſt by <hi>Warwicke</hi> and <hi>Watling-ſtreet:</hi> the North is ſeuered from <hi>Lincolne-ſhire</hi> by the Riuer <hi>Weland;</hi> and <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> and <hi>Buckingham-ſhires</hi> incloſe it on the South. It containes in length (from <hi>Cherwell</hi> to <hi>Weland</hi> Riuer neere <hi>Crowland</hi>) 46 miles, and at the broadeſt (betweene the Riuers of <hi>Ouſe</hi> and <hi>Auon</hi>) neere 20, the whole circuit being about 119 miles. Into 20 Hundreds is this Shire ſhared, which containe in them 326 Pariſh Churches: and with fiue Riuers is it watered, which are paſſeable by 24 Bridges. Moreouer with three Foreſts and 23 Parkes is this County delighted. For Traffique and Trade amongſt the Inhabitants, there are ſeated ſeuerally 11 Market Townes, whereof the Shire-Towne <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton</hi> (whence the County carries the name) is of moſt account, being both large in quantitie, and beautifull in qualitie; for it is adorned with many faire and ſtately buildings, it is pleaſantly ſeated on the Riuer <hi>Nene,</hi> and (excepting on the Riuers ſide) was anciently ſtrongly walled with ſtone; but <hi>Suen</hi> the <hi>Daniſh</hi> King firſt fired it, and after that in King <hi>Iohns</hi> time the diſloyall Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons afflicted it, ſince when hath it not beene free from cruell Fortunes bitter blaſts. The ruines of (her ſometime ſtrong defence) the Caſtle ſtand weather beaten vpon a mount on the Weſt part of the Towne, to ſhew what it had beene. This Towne is ciuilly gouerned by an annuall elected Maior, two Bailiffes, 12 Magiſtrates, and a Recorder; the Pole being eleuated 52. 16. and the Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude 23. 44. In this County alſo is ſeated the Citie of <hi>Peterborough,</hi> which by the <hi>Saxons</hi> was called <hi>Meddeſwell,</hi> where was a mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Monaſterie built and dedicated to <hi>S. Peter</hi> by the <hi>Mercian</hi> King <hi>Wolphere;</hi> which though it be now ruinated, yet is there a moſt faire and ſtately Cathedrall, hauing a large Cloyſter, in the glaſſe windowes whereof the hiſtorie of <hi>Wolphere</hi> the Founder is moſt curiouſly figured. This County hath beene fortified for defence with ten ſtrong and famous Caſtles, and likewiſe plentifully ſtored with the foundations of many faire and rich Religious Houſes, which for their magnificall ſtate in time of their ſtanding, were as ſo many beautifull ornaments to the Shire; whereas now their duſt and ruines are but motiues of pittie to all that paſſe by them. The Aire in this Prouince is temperate, pleaſant, and healthfull; and the Soile fat, rich, and fertile, producing all kinde of the beſt Corne: And for delightfull Medowes, cheerefull Woods, and pleaſant Paſtures, the Inhabitants are ſo plentifully furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as their herds of cattell and faire flocks of ſheepe (which both for fleſh and fleece cannot be bettered) doe ſo infinitely multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie, as thereby the Countrey is befitted with all kinde of vſefull and neceſſary commodities in an abundant manner.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:33"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Northamptonshire</figDesc>
                     <head>Northamton Shire</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Bedfordshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:34"/>
               <head>Bedford-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Shire taketh the name from the Shire-Towne, called by vs <hi>Bedford,</hi> from the <hi>Saxon</hi> name <hi>Bedenford,</hi> but by the <hi>Britaines</hi> it was called <hi>Lettidur.</hi> This County is bordered on the North ſide with <hi>Huntington-ſhire,</hi> on the South with <hi>Buckingham</hi> and <hi>Hartford-ſhires,</hi> on the Eaſt with <hi>Hartford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge-ſhires,</hi> and vpon the Weſt with <hi>Northampton</hi> and <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingham-ſhires.</hi> It is but a ſmall Continent, being in length (from <hi>Tilbrooke</hi> North to <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> South) about 24 miles, and the bredth (from <hi>Turney</hi> Weſt to <hi>Hatley Coking</hi> in the Eaſt) ſcarce 14 miles, which cauſeth the circumference to make in all not aboue 73 miles. It is diſtinguiſhed into nine Hundreds, wherein are 116 Pariſh-Churches. Only one Riuer (which is <hi>Ouſe</hi>) watereth this Shire, which is ouerpaſſed but by ſix Bridges. It hath intercourſe for the traffique of commodities with ten Market Townes, whereof that at <hi>Bedford</hi> (the moſt famous) is moſt pleaſantly ſeated, in a moſt fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoile, hauing the Riuer <hi>Ouſe</hi> diuiding the Towne in the midſt, ouer which is built a faire and ſtrong ſtone Bridge, with two Gates, for the preuention of paſſage if need ſhould require. And here on the brinke of this Riuer ſometime ſtood a little Chapell, wherein (as ancient Writers record) <hi>Offa</hi> the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> King was buried, whoſe Monument a long time there remained, till the ouerflowing Riuer waſhed it cleane away. This Towne hath a Maior, two Bailiffes, two Chamberlaines, and a Recorder, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne it: the Longitude there being 24. 0. and the Eleuation of the Pole for Latitude 52. 11. At <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable</hi> in this Shire, and <hi>Sandey,</hi> which were then called <hi>Magintum</hi> and <hi>Selenae,</hi> lay the <hi>Roman</hi> Legions, where to this day are found diuers ſorts of their Coynes. And afterwards hence did the <hi>Saxons</hi> driue out the <hi>Britaines,</hi> and ſeated themſelues in their roome. At a place neere <hi>Harwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d (Anno</hi> 1399) the Riuer <hi>Ouſe</hi> ſtood ſuddenly ſtill, ſo as men went three miles in the bottome of the Channell on foot without any danger. This Shire alſo hath beene beautified with diuers faire Caſtles, as at <hi>Woodhill, Temsford, Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> and <hi>Amphill,</hi> and many famous Houſes of Religion, which are now vtterly aboliſhed and laid leuell with their foundations. The Aire here is very temperate and pleaſant bringing both delight and health to the Inhabitants. The Soile is rich and fertile, but eſpecially where the Riuer <hi>Ouſe</hi> by the moiſtening of her bankes makes the meadowes ſend forth their increaſe in abundance. And although the other parts of the Shire are ſomewhat more barren, being for the moſt part a Champion, yet by the induſtrious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants it is well ſtored with Barly, and plenty of Paſturage, and is not wanting for ſome ſtore of Woods.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:34"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Bedfordshire</figDesc>
                     <head>BEDFORD SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Huntingdonshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:35"/>
               <head>Huntington-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Vntington-ſhire,</hi> which was called by the Ancients <hi>Hundedumſcyre,</hi> is enuironed with <hi>Lincoln</hi> &amp; <hi>Northampton-ſhires</hi> on the North, <hi>Bedford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge-ſhires</hi> on the South, the Ile of <hi>Ely</hi> on the Eaſt, and <hi>Northampton-ſhire</hi> on the Weſt. It reacheth in length (from <hi>Tetworth</hi> South to <hi>Woodſtone</hi> North) not aboue 20 miles, &amp; from <hi>Erith</hi> Eaſt to <hi>Keſton</hi> Weſt (where it is broadeſt) much about 16. In the time of the <hi>Romans</hi> it was part of the <hi>Iceni,</hi> &amp; vnder the <hi>Saxons</hi> part of <hi>Mercia,</hi> which till <hi>Canutus</hi> time was all Foreſt. This Shire in ancient time had 5, but now is diſtinguiſhed into but 4 diuiſions, called the Hundreds of <hi>Norman Croſſe, Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Leightenſtone,</hi> and <hi>Toſland,</hi> which are ſubdiuided into 79 Pariſhes, which are meaſured by Hides and Carucks or plowed lands; and they are interlaced and irriguated with the Riuer <hi>Ouſe,</hi> and diuers other Riuerets beſides, the Fens &amp; Marſh grounds ſtretching towards <hi>Lincolne-ſhire</hi> and the Ile of <hi>Ely.</hi> And for commerce and traffique amongſt the Inhabitants, this County (being not very big) containeth but ſix Market Townes, wherof <hi>Huntington</hi> the Shire-Towne and denominator of the whole County, is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the chiefe, which in old time was called <hi>Hundendun,</hi> or <hi>The Hunters Downe,</hi> and is ſituate on the North banke of the Riuer <hi>Ouſe,</hi> on the riſing of a hill, and in former ages had in it 15 Churches, which are now ſuppreſſed with their own ruines, except <hi>S. Maries</hi> &amp; 3 others. This Town in the time of the Conqueror was diuided into 4 Wards, wherin were contained 256 houſholds: and here was money coyned, hauing on the one ſide the image &amp; ſtile of the King, and on the other ſide the name of the Earle or B ſhop then being in the time of the coynage. The Caſtle alſo is now vtterly ruinated, which by ſome is thought to be built by <hi>Edw.</hi> the elder, &amp; the ſeat of the great <hi>Saxon</hi> Earle <hi>Waltheol,</hi> but raſed down by <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. Here <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> Earle of <hi>Anguiſe</hi> built the Hoſpitall of <hi>S. Iohn Bapt.</hi> &amp; with many other Monaſteries and religious hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes was as well this Towne as the whole County adorned. The Riuer to this Towne was once nauigable, till <hi>Grey</hi> the Kings Fauourite ſtopt vp the paſſage: and by Charter from <hi>K. Iohn</hi> is the gouernment hereof co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to 2 yeerely elected Bailiffes &amp; a Recorder, with ſome other Aſſiſtants. The Pole being eleuated 52. 23. and the Longitude 24. 21. The many rich and ſtately Monaſteries and Religious Houſes in this County were by K. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. laid leuell with their foundations, and in their owne ruines entombed. This Prouince on the Weſt ſide is more hillie and healthfull than the other toward the Fenns and Marſhes, and yeeldeth ſtore of corne and other vſefull commodities: and the lower watery grounds are equall to any part of <hi>England</hi> for goodneſſe of feeding, and the beſt paſturage, beſides plenty of Turfe and Fuell from the Moores and Mariſh grounds. So, as well as any other Shire, is this County accommodated with Corne, Fleſh, Fowle, and Fiſh, and wants almoſt nothing that is neceſſary.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:35"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Huntingdonshire</figDesc>
                     <head>HVNTINGTON SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Cambridgeshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:36"/>
               <head>Cambridge-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Engliſh Saxons</hi> called this County <hi>Grentbrig-ſcyre,</hi> which wee call <hi>Cambridge-ſhire,</hi> and is bordered vpon on the Eaſt with <hi>Suffolke</hi> and <hi>Norfolke,</hi> on the Weſt with <hi>Huntingdon</hi> and <hi>Bedford ſhires,</hi> on the North with <hi>Norfolke</hi> and <hi>Lincolne-ſhire,</hi> and on the South with <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Hartford-ſhire.</hi> The length of it (from the furtheſt of the Fenns in the North, to <hi>Royſton</hi> South) containes 35 miles, and the bredth at the broadeſt from Eaſt to Weſt, is ſcarce 20. and the whole compaſſe being meaſured with her many turnings, amounts to 128 miles. It is but a ſmall Shire, and yet is diuided into 17 Hundreds, which haue in them 165 Pariſh-Churches, and eight Market Townes, whereof the moſt famous and euer flouriſhing Vniuerſitie of <hi>Cambridge</hi> is the principall, which is ſituate on the Eaſt ſide of the Riuer <hi>Caine,</hi> from whence (as ſome hold) ſhe hath her name; although other Hiſtories of antiquitie deriue it from <hi>Cantaber,</hi> who 375 yeeres before the Incarnation had there ſetled the Muſes ſeat. And albeit in many Ages this Citie (like many others) hath taſted many wofull fortunes, yet now is it beautified and fairely adorned with ſixteene moſt magnificent Colleges and Halls, full ſtored with painfull Students, and as euer it hath, ſo ſtill it doth with abundant increaſe of moſt learned and famous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Teachers, and Profeſſors of all Arts and Sciences, enrich not only this our Land, but all others whereto they are diſperſed. The Eleuation of the Pole is here 52. 17. degrees, and Longitude 24. 46. Another Citie in this Shire was ſometime alſo of great note, called by the <hi>Saxons Elg,</hi> but now by vs <hi>Ely,</hi> which grew firſt famous for one <hi>Audrey</hi> a Princeſſe, and wife to <hi>Egbert</hi> King of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> who there built a Nunnery, and leauing her husband, was the firſt Abbeſſe of it her ſelfe. Yet this alſo eſcaped not the fury of misfortune, for afterwards by the <hi>Danes</hi> was it vtterly ruinated, till <hi>Ethelwold</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> repaired it, and built there a Monaſterie for Monkes. And though it be now alſo diſſolued, yet is there remaining the ſtately Cathedrall of that Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. This County hath had many faire foundations of rich Religious Houſes, as at <hi>Beach, Barnwell, Charteres, Denny, Elſey, Shengey, Swaſey,</hi> and <hi>Thorney:</hi> but theſe as well as the reſt were ſuppreſt and depreſt with the weight of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighths hand. Amongſt the remarkable things in this County, <hi>Gogmagog Hills</hi> is one, which is neere vnto <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and was a Fort with a Treble Trench raiſed there by the <hi>Danes,</hi> whoſe Station it then was. And another was a long and large Trench, paſſing quite thorow <hi>Newmarket Heath,</hi> which is commonly called <hi>The Deuils Ditch,</hi> but at firſt was made there to defend the <hi>Eaſt-Angles</hi> againſt the <hi>Mercians,</hi> as our ancient Hiſtories doe record. The Fenns on the North of this County doe make the Aire neither ſo pleaſant nor wholeſome as it is in other Shires: but more Southerly it is much more delectable. And as in it, ſo is there a difference in the Soile, which on the South is Feilden, and being watered with the Riuer <hi>Came,</hi> is fraught with faire Medowes and Paſtures, and yeeldeth plenty of Corne, ſome Saffron, and Woods: The Fenny part being exceedingly repleniſhed with abundant ſtore both of Fiſh and Fowle.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:36"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Cambridgeshire</figDesc>
                     <head>CAMBRIDGE SHIRE AND ISLE OF ELY</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Suffolk" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:37"/>
               <head>Suffolke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His County was tearmed by the <hi>Saxons Suthfole,</hi> and is bounded on the Eaſt with the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Seas, on the Weſt with the County of <hi>Cambridge;</hi> the South ſide by <hi>Stowre</hi> is ſeuered from <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and the North from <hi>Norfolke</hi> by the Riuers of <hi>Waueney</hi> and the leſſer <hi>Ouſe.</hi> The length (being from <hi>Eaſton point</hi> Eaſt to the Riuer of great <hi>Ouſe</hi> Weſt) 45 miles; and at the broadeſt part (betweene North and South) hath but about 20. which cauſeth the whole compaſſe to containe much vpon 146 miles. The diuiſion of this Shire is in three parts, <hi>viz. Celdable, S. Edmunds,</hi> and <hi>S. Audries,</hi> which are ſubdiuided into 22 Hundreds, and containe in them 575 Pariſh-Churches. Beſides ſmall Streames, it is watered but with two Riuers, which haue ouer them 32 Bridges. The Inhabitants doe trade for commodities in this County in 28 Market Townes, the chiefeſt whereof is <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> a faire and ſtately Towne for buildings, being ſeated moſt pleaſantly in a fruitfull Soile, and well traded with all kinde of merchantable commodities. It ſeemes to haue beene walled about in times paſt, and to haue had Gates for entrance, where is now but ſmall appearance thereof, being caſt downe by the <hi>Danes,</hi> who raſed the whole Towne to the ground; but afterwards it reuiued, and was beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully rebuilt, with many large ſtreets, and diuers faire Churches, whereof 12 doe yet remaine, beſides thoſe that are diſſolued. It is a Corporation orderly gouerned by two yeerely elected Bailiffes, 10 Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, 24 of the Common Counſell, and a Recorder. And the height of the Pole is there 52. 4 and Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude 25. 52. And their ancient Towne of note in this County is that which euer ſince the buriall of King <hi>Edmund</hi> (who was ſhot to death at <hi>Hoxon</hi>) is therefore called <hi>S. Edmunds Bury,</hi> where for that Kings perpetuall memory was built one of the moſt magnificent Abbies that euer was founded; yet now (like the reſt) it lies ouerwhelmed with the huge heapes of her owne ruines. Betweene <hi>Alborough</hi> and <hi>Orford, Anno</hi> 1555 (in the time of a violent famine) miraculouſly ſprung vp great plenty of Peaſe on the Rocks, without either ſowing or tillage, to the wonderfull releefe of the diſtreſſed Inhabitants of this County. Diuers moſt magnificent and faire Religious Houſes haue beene in diuers places ſituate in this Shire, which are depreſſed. And many other places and accidents remarkable doth this County af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, which to keepe my ſelfe within my limited bounds, I am forced to omit. The Aire is here freſh, pleaſant, and healthfull; the Soile rich, fat, and fruitfull, producing Paſture, Corne, Cattell, Woods, Wools, Cloth, and Fiſh and Fowles in abundance.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:37"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Suffolke</figDesc>
                     <head>SUFFOLKE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Norfolke" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:38"/>
               <head>Norfolke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe this County was the furtheſt North part of the Kingdome of the <hi>Eaſt-Angles,</hi> it was tearmed <hi>Northfolke,</hi> which wee call <hi>Norfolke,</hi> and is bounded on the Eaſt and North with the German Seas, on the South it is ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from <hi>Suffolke</hi> with the Riuers of <hi>Waueney</hi> and the leſſer <hi>Ouſe,</hi> and on the Weſt it butts vpon <hi>Lincolne</hi> and <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge-ſhires.</hi> It ſtretcheth in length (from <hi>Yarmouth</hi> Eaſt to <hi>Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bitch</hi> Weſt) neere 50 miles, and the bredth (from <hi>Wells</hi> to <hi>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ford</hi>) 30, making the circumference to containe much vpon 242 miles. It is diuided into 32 Hundreds, and theſe are ſubdiuided into 660 Pariſh-Churches. Beſides, many good Harbours and diuers faire Riuers and Streames interlace this County, which are paſſable by 15 Bridges. And for traffique of merchandize and other commodities, it is conueniently fitted with 30 Market Townes, whereof the faireſt is the famous Citie of <hi>Norwich,</hi> which though like others it hath taſted varietie of fortunes, yet is it now for beauty and abilitie counted the beſt next LONDON of any other City in <hi>England,</hi> being delectably placed in a pleaſant bottome vpon the Riuer <hi>Hierus,</hi> and yet vpon the aſcent of an hill, which on the Eaſt ſide mounts ſo high, as to ouerlooke the whole Citie. In King <hi>Stephens</hi> time it was made a Corporation; <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt fortified it with a wall, except on that ſide next the Riuer; and <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth made it a County, and changed the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from foure Bailiffes to a Maior: and though many of the ancient Churches and Religious Houſes lie now waſted in their owne ruines, yet ſtill doth it containe about 30 Pariſhes. On the Eaſt ſide of this County is ſituate <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> at the mouth of the Riuer <hi>Yere,</hi> from whence it hath the name; and by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third was walled and made a Corporation. It is ſtrongly built, and well fortified, being the chiefe of the Cinque-ports, where about September euery yeere is great fiſhing for Herrings, as the like is not in any part of <hi>Europe,</hi> whereby the Towne for the preſent, and the whole Land (with diuers other) all the yeere after is both enriched and refreſhed. Another remarkable Towne in this Shire is <hi>Lyn,</hi> which was made a Corporation by King <hi>Iohn,</hi> who gaue them a Cup, which ſtill remaineth there as a memorable teſtimonie of his bounty: but afterwards by King <hi>Henry</hi> the third was their Charter enlarged, and their Bailiffe altered to a Maior, by whom (with Aſſiſtants of twelue Aldermen and a Recorder) it is at this day gouerned. About <hi>Thetford</hi> in this County, by <hi>Hungar</hi> and <hi>Hubba</hi> the <hi>Danes</hi> was good King <hi>Edmund</hi> ouerthrowne, who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward was martyred at <hi>S. Edmunds Bury.</hi> By reaſon of this Shires ſo neere neighbouring to the Seas, the Aire is ſomewhat ſharpe and piercing. The Eleuation of the Pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being there 52. 46. 1/2. and the Longitude 25. 57. The Soile as in ſome places it is leane and barren, ſo is it in other parts fat and fruitfull, but in all places very commodious to the Inhabitants, for <hi>Marſland</hi> is excellent good for Paſture, and <hi>Flegg</hi> for Corne. The Weſt part along the Coaſt is their Champion, and yeeldeth great ſtore of Sheepe, Corne, and Conies: and that part more within Land (being more wooddie) is their Woodland, which is ſo ſtored with graſſe, as it furniſheth the Country with plenty of Cattell, and yet is not wanting for Corne or Sheepe. And generally all over doth it abound both for Fiſh and Fowle, with many other vſefull commodities.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:38"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Norfolk</figDesc>
                     <head>NORFOLKE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Lincolnshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:39"/>
               <head>Lincolne-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Shire was called by the <hi>Saxons Lincollſcyre,</hi> by the <hi>Normans Nicolſhire,</hi> and now vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly <hi>Lincolne-ſhire.</hi> It is a very large County, extending in length (from <hi>Barton</hi> vpon <hi>Humber</hi> in the North, to <hi>Stanford</hi> on the Riuer <hi>Nyne</hi> in the South) 55 miles, and in bredth (from <hi>Newton</hi> in the Weſt to <hi>Winthorpe</hi> in the Eaſt) 35 miles, the whole circuit being about 180 miles. It is enuironed on the North with the Riuer <hi>Humber,</hi> on the Eaſt with the German Sea; on the South it butteth on the Counties of <hi>Northampton</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and on the Weſt vpon <hi>Nottingham</hi> and <hi>Yorke-ſhires.</hi> It is diuided into three principall parts, <hi>Lindſey, Keſteuen,</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; Lindſey</hi> containing 17 Hundreds, <hi>Keſteuen</hi> 11, and <hi>Holland</hi> 3, in all 31 Hundreds, wherein are 630 Pariſh-Churches. This Shire hath alſo in it nine Riuers, and fifteene Bridges: and though on the Eaſt and South ſides of it (by reaſon of the Fenns) the Aire is ſomewhat foggie, yet is it temperate. And it is ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated to the height of 53 degrees. This County is ſomewhat vnſafe for Trauellers, for the Sands and Salt waters which in many places make incurſions into the Land. It is traded with 31 Market Townes, whereof the Citie of <hi>Lincolne</hi> (the denomination of the County) is the chiefe. The antiquitie of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie appeareth as well by the ſtill remaining ruines, as by the ancient Records. In one whereof is read, that this Citie had in it 1007 Manſions, 900 Burgeſſes, and 12 Lage-men. In the <hi>Normans</hi> time it was the moſt populous of any City of <hi>England,</hi> and in it did King <hi>Edward</hi> 3 ordaine his ſtaple for the mart of Wools. Leather, and Lead; in whoſe raigne it was adorned with 50 Pariſh-Churches, but now (beſides the Chathedrall) it hath but 15. It is gouerned with a Maior, 2 Sheriffes, 12 Aldermen, and a Recorder. It is ſeated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n a hill, and hath for Longitude 23. 48. and for Latitude 53. 17. This County towards the North and Weſt is very pleaſant, rich, and fertile, both for Arable, Paſture, and Medow; and on the South and Eaſt it excells all other parts of this Realme for plentie of Fiſh and Fowle. Learned <hi>M. Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> reports, that at <hi>Harlaxton</hi> in this Shire (in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth) was plowed vp a Brazen Veſſell, wherein was an Helmet of gold of a very ancient faſhion, beſet with many pretious ſtones. This Shire hath heretofore beene adorned with many Religious Houſes, which are now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to ruines. And the chiefe commodities of this County are Cattell, Corne, Fiſh, Fowle, Alabla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and Flax.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:39"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Lincolnshire</figDesc>
                     <head>THE COUN<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>TIE OF LINCOLNE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Rutland" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:40"/>
               <head>Rutland-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Rutland-ſhire,</hi> which (as ſome hold) beares the name from one <hi>Rut,</hi> that rod about the whole Shire in one day; but others affirme it was firſt ſo called by the old <hi>Engliſh Saxons,</hi> for the re neſſe of the earth, ſeeing the word <hi>Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or <hi>Roet</hi> in their language, is as much as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in ours; and for that the naturall ſoile is indeed ſo red, that it often colours the wooll of the ſheepe into a reddiſh die. It i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the leaſt of all the reſt of the Shires in <hi>England,</hi> which on the Eaſt and South by the Riuer <hi>Wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd</hi> is diuided from <hi>Northampton-ſhire,</hi> the Weſt ſide being bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered vpon by <hi>L <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>caſter- h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and the North by <hi>Lincolne-ſhire.</hi> It containes in length (from <hi>Caldecor</hi> South on the Riuer <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fartheſt part North at a little Towne called <hi>Thiſtleton</hi>) not altogether a dozen miles; and from <hi>Timwell</hi> in the Eaſt to <hi>Wiſſenden</hi> Weſt (which is the broadeſt part) neere vnto nine miles: ſo as the whole County is much about forty miles compaſſe. It is diuided into 5 Hundreds. viz. <hi>Eaſt, Allſtoe, O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ham, W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anged,</hi> and <hi>Martinſley;</hi> and theſe are ſubdiuided into but 48 Pariſhes. There are foure Parkes in this County, and but two Market Townes for commerce of commodities; which cauſeth the Inhabitants (for their better aduantage) to trauell to others in the Shires next adioyning: but of the two, <hi>Ok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ham</hi> is the beſt and faireſt, which ſtands not farre from <hi>Burley,</hi> that famous and ſtately houſe of the right honourable the Lord <hi>Harrington,</hi> who in this Lordſhip of <hi>Okeham</hi> had ſuch an extraordinary Royaltie, that if any Noble man came at any time within the precinct of it, he was to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet an homage horſe-ſhooe from the Steed whereon he rode, or elſe to redeeme it at a price in money: and for a true confirmation thereof, a man may ſee many horſe-ſhooes faſtened on the doore of the Shire-Hall, whereof ſome are large and of ancient faſhion. The Towne is large, and the Church faire. And here alſo hath beene a Caſtle of defence, which ſeemes by the ruines to haue beene of great ſtrength. The Eleuati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of the Pole is here 52. 45. and the Longitude 23. 48. King <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor gaue this County to <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th</hi> his Queene, and after her death to the Monaſterie at <hi>Weſtminſter:</hi> but <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror cancelled it, and beſtowed the lands vpon others. The <hi>Coritani</hi> (according to <hi>Ptolemy</hi>) were the ancient Inhabitants of this County, which for aire and health is as good, pleaſant and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as any other place of the Land, and (for the quantitie) hath as fertile a Soile, which for tillage may compare with the beſt. Woods are here good ſtore, and both hills and pleaſant bottomes watered with many freſh Springs, are not wanting, which bring forth abundance of Corne, and with ſtocks of ſheepe and herds of Neat are plentifully ſtored.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:40"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Rutland</figDesc>
                     <head>RUTLAND SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Leicestershire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:41"/>
               <head>Leiceſter-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Shire for the bounds hath <hi>Lincolne</hi> and <hi>Rutland-ſhires</hi> on the Eaſt, and on the Weſt the way called <hi>Watling-ſtreet</hi> diuides it from <hi>Warwicke-ſhire; Nottingham-ſhire</hi> imbordereth on the North, and <hi>Northampton-ſhire</hi> on the South. It is neere as broad as long; for the full length in her greateſt Longitude (from Eaſt to Weſt) is not altogether thirty miles, and the bredth (from North to South) is twenty foure, which makes the whole circumference much vpon 196 miles. The diuiſion of it is into ſix Hundreds, namely, <hi>Sparkingho, Framland, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxton, Gartrey, Eaſt Goſcote,</hi> and <hi>Weſt Goſcote,</hi> which doe containe in them 200 Pariſh-Churches. This Shire is watered but with one Riuer of note, (beſides ſmall brookes) namely <hi>Stowre,</hi> yet hath ten Bridges; and in it are alſo contained two Foreſts, and fifteene Parkes. A doſen of Market Townes are here and there diſperſed in this County, for the Inhabitants traffique and commerce, whereof the chiefeſt is the Shire-Towne <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> which (as our old Hiſtories record) in ancient times was called <hi>Legeceſtria,</hi> and by <hi>Ninus, Caer-Leri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> being built 844 yeeres before the birth of our Sauiour, by King <hi>Leir,</hi> who there erected the Temple of <hi>Ianus,</hi> and in it placed a Flamine, and after (as it is recorded) was therein him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe interred. But long after this did <hi>Ethelred</hi> the King of the <hi>Mercians</hi> make it an Epiſcopall Sea, wherein he made <hi>Sexwulph</hi> the firſt Biſhop. But in proceſſe of time, the Biſhopricke being thence tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, and the Towne brought to a low ebbe, <hi>Edelfred</hi> repaired and fortified it with a ſtrong wall, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there is now no memoriall but by ſome of the old ruines; for <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond both vtterly raſed the Caſtle, and fired the Towne. It is ſituate on the Riuer <hi>Stowre,</hi> neere the very midſt of the Shire. And the Eleuation of the Pole is there 52. 41. and the Longitude 23. 32. In the yeere 1485 the 22 day of Auguſt, neere <hi>Market Boſworth,</hi> was King <hi>Richard</hi> the Third ſlaine, with 4000 men, in a battell fought by King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth, who thereby happily ended the long and wofull contention betweene the two Houſes of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter:</hi> and the Vſurpers body deſpightfully mangled, laid naked on a horſe backe, and ſo carried to <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and was there buried in the <hi>Gray Friers.</hi> The Aire in this County is milde, pleaſant, and healthfull: The Soile towards the South and Eaſt (which is moſt Champion) is not ſo wooddie as the North, (where Pit-cole for fuell is gotten in abundance) yeeldeth great ſtore of Corne: So as the chiefe commodities here are Cattell, Corne, and Pit-cole. And yet for other neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, they are nothing wanting.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:41"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Leicestershire</figDesc>
                     <head>LEICESTER SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Staffordshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:42"/>
               <head>Stafford-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His County, which wee call <hi>Staff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd-ſhire,</hi> was ſo called alſo by the <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh Saxons,</hi> and is incloſed on the Eaſt with the Riuers of <hi>Dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Trent,</hi> which diuide it from <hi>Darby-ſhire;</hi> and on the Weſt with <hi>Shro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhire: Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhire</hi> and <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>by-ſhires</hi> confine it on the North, and <hi>Warwicke</hi> and <hi>Worceſter-ſhires</hi> on the South. The length is meaſured (from North to South) 44 miles, and the bredth (from Eaſt to Weſt) 27, making the whole circumference to containe 140 miles. It is diuided into fiue Hundreds, and they are ſubdiuided into 130 Pariſhes. There is in it alſo one Citie, one Chaſe, one Foreſt, and 38 Parkes. Thirteene Riuers doe irriguate this County, which haue ouer them nineteene Bridges. And for commerce and traffique, it is traded in thirteene Market Townes, whereof <hi>Stafford</hi> the Shire-Towne is accounted one of the chiefeſt, which was anciently called <hi>Beth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ney,</hi> from the holy Hermite <hi>Bertlin,</hi> that there liued. It hath in times paſt on the Eaſt and South ſides beene fortified both with a Wall and Trench, and on the oppoſite ſides had a ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ange defence of water, which now by time is transformed into faire and pleaſant meadowes. Foure Gates (according to the foure Cardinall points) doe make way for paſſage into this Towne, which is ſeated on the North ſide of the Riuer <hi>Sowe,</hi> and is ciuilly and orderly gouerned by two yeerely elected Bailiſſes out of the Common Counſell, conſiſting of 21 Aſſiſtants. The Pole is here eleuated to 52. 53. and the Longitude 22. 29. In this Shire alſo is ſeated <hi>Lichfield,</hi> which is both of greater antiquitie, and farre more famous than <hi>Stafford;</hi> and which by <hi>Beda</hi> was called <hi>Licedfeld,</hi> ſignifying a field of dead carkaſſes, which (as ſome hold) was ſo termed of a great number of Saints there ſlaine by <hi>Diocleſian.</hi> In this Citie did <hi>Oſwn</hi> King of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland</hi> build a Church, and made it a Biſhops Sea, which afterwards was by meanes of King <hi>Oſſa,</hi> and <hi>Adrian</hi> the Pope, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced to the dignitie of an Archbiſhopricke: and in this Church were the bodies of <hi>Wolphere</hi> and <hi>Celred,</hi> two <hi>Mercian</hi> Kings, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. This Citie at this day is gouerned by two Bailiffes, and one Sheriffe, which from 24 Burgeſſes are annually elected. By <hi>Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemy,</hi> the ancient Inhabitants of this County were the <hi>Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ij,</hi> but afterwards it became part of the <hi>Mercian Saxons</hi> poſſeſſion, whoſe Kings palace was then ſeated at the Towne of <hi>Tamworth.</hi> Many famous and faire Religious Houſes, that a long time flouriſhed, haue beene raiſed vp in this County: but in continuance of time (as well as others in other Shires) haue beene raſed downe and buried in their owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uines. And with thirteene ſtrong Caſtles alſo was it once guarded, whereof now but few remaine ſo much as for an ornament to the County. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ire here (though toward the North ſomewhat freſh and ſharpe) is very healthfull; and the Soile on the South fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uitfull, but on the North more barren, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſon of Moores and Hills there ſeated; yet is the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle both well woodded, and watered with many pleaſant Riuers, yeelding great plenty of Fiſh, as well as the whole County doth of Fleſh, and other neceſſary commodities, as namely of Corne, Cattell, Woods, Pit-cole, Iron, and Alablaſter.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:42"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Staffordshire</figDesc>
                     <head>STAFFORD SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Derbyshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:43"/>
               <head>Darby-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Arby-ſhire</hi> (which the old <hi>Saxons</hi> called <hi>Deorbyrſcire</hi>) is on the Eaſt incloſed with <hi>Nottingham-ſhire,</hi> on the South with <hi>Leiceſter-ſhire,</hi> on the Weſt with <hi>Stafford-ſhire,</hi> and with <hi>Yorke-ſhire</hi> on the North, the Riuer <hi>Derwent</hi> (as it were) diuiding it, falleth into <hi>Trent,</hi> which ouerthwarteth the South point of the Shire. The Eaſt and South parts are very fruitfull, hauing many Parkes in them; but the Weſt (called the <hi>Peake</hi>) which is hillie, ſtonie, and craggie, is more barren, yet hath it much Lead, Iron, and Coles, and is very good for the keeping of ſheepe. On the Weſt ſide of <hi>Derwent</hi> is ſeated <hi>Darby</hi> the chiefeſt Towne of the Shire, which by the <hi>Danes</hi> was called <hi>Deoraby,</hi> of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Derwent,</hi> contracted from <hi>Derwentby,</hi> as ancient <hi>Athelward</hi> records. This Towne is of a reaſonable bigneſſe, hauing good trade and reſort vnto it; the Riuer hauing a beautifull ſtone Bridge ouer it in the North-Eaſt of the Towne, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon was erected a faire Chapell, which is now decaying, beſides which there are fiue Churches in the Towne, the greateſt whereof (called <hi>All-Hallowes</hi>) is famous both for the height of the Tower, and the excellencie of the workmanſhip. And cloſe by it the Counteſſe of <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> hath founded an Hoſpitall for the maintenance of eight men and foure women. This Towne is gouerned with two Bailiffes, choſen out of 24 brethren, and as many Burgeſſes, and a Towne-Clarke: The Eleuation of the Pole being there 55. 5. and the Longitude 23. 7. This was the Rendeuous for the <hi>Danes,</hi> till <hi>Ethelfleda</hi> the <hi>Mercian</hi> Lady by ſurpriſing and ſlaughtering of them, became Miſtreſſe of it. And in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor it had 143 Burgeſſes. This Shire is in forme of a Triangle, the length (from North to South) containing 38 miles, and the bredth in the broadeſt part neere 29 miles, the circumference being about 130 miles. It is diuided into ſix Hundreds, wherein are 106 Pariſh-Churches. It hath commerce with eight Market Townes, and hath had ſeuen Caſtles, with eight foundations of Religious Houſes and Monaſteries. It hath ſtore of Woods, Cattell, and Corne, with Mines of Lead, Milſtone, Cole, and Stibium. At a place called <hi>Buxtons,</hi> in eight yards com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe ariſe nine Springs, eight warme, and one cold, neere which alſo is another hot Spring from a Well called <hi>S. Anne of Buxtons,</hi> and cloſe by it another cold Spring; the waters of all which are reported to performe many ſtrange Cures. Not farre hence is a place called <hi>Elden Hole,</hi> being of a huge wideneſſe, very ſteepe, and of a wonderfull depth. And about ſeuen miles from it is an old Caſtle, called <hi>The Caſtle in the Peake,</hi> vnder which is a hole tearmed <hi>The Deuils Arſe,</hi> which in the entrance is very wide, hauing many turnings and retiring roomes in it, and is accounted for one of our Engliſh wonders. In <hi>Peake Foreſt</hi> neere <hi>Buxtons</hi> is a Well which ebbeth and floweth foure times an houre.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:43"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Derbyshire</figDesc>
                     <head>DARBY SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Nottinghamshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:44"/>
               <head>Nottingham-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ottingham-ſhire</hi> is ſo called from <hi>Nottingham</hi> the chiefe Towne, and it is bounded on the North and North-weſt with the County of <hi>Yorke,</hi> on the Eaſt with <hi>Lincolne-ſhire,</hi> the South ſide being confined with <hi>Leiceſter-ſhire,</hi> and with <hi>Darby-ſhire</hi> on the Weſt. It is extended from <hi>Fimingly</hi> North to <hi>Steanford</hi> in the South, 38 miles, and from <hi>Teuerſall</hi> Weſt to <hi>Beeſthorpe</hi> Eaſt, about 20 miles, the whole compaſſe being 110 miles. This Shire is diuided into two parts, called by the Inhabitants <hi>The Sand</hi> and <hi>The Clay;</hi> and theſe are ſubdiuided into eight Wapentacks, which containe in them 168 Pariſh-Churches. This County is traffiqued with eight Market Townes for commerce, whereof the beſt and greateſt is <hi>Nottingham,</hi> which is moſt pleaſantly ſituated on a high hill, adorned with ſtately buildings, and for many faire ſtreets much excelling diuers other greater Cities. The Market-place is large and faire. Many Caues and Vaults are in the Towne, which are hewen out of the Rocke, but the moſt famous of them are thoſe vnder the Caſtle, whereof one hath the ſtory of Chriſts paſsion engrauen on the walls by <hi>Dauid</hi> the Second King of <hi>Scots,</hi> being there held priſoner; and another wherein Lord <hi>Mortimer</hi> was ſurpriſed by King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, for which cauſe it is ſtill called <hi>Mortimers Hole.</hi> The Roomes and Staires of theſe are made out of the Rock, the Caſtle it ſelfe being ſtrong. King <hi>Edward</hi> ſurnamed the Elder compaſſed this Towne with a Wall, whereof but a little doth now remaine, the reſt being turned to ruines. The compaſſe of this Towne (according to <hi>M. Speed</hi>) is 2120 paſes. And it is gouerned by a Maior, two Sheriffes, two Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines, and ſix Aldermen: The Pole being there eleuated 52. 58. and Longitude 23. 35. This County is pleaſant, and wholſome for Aire; Clayie, Sandie, and rich for Soile; very fruitfull both for Corne and Graſſe, being plentifully ſtored with Wood, Water, and Cole. In this Shire groweth a Stone, which being not ſo hard as <hi>Alablaſter,</hi> maketh a Plaſter harder than <hi>Plaſter of Paris,</hi> wherewith they vſe to floore their vpper roomes. At a place neere <hi>Workſopp</hi> in this Shire is planted much and very good Liquorice. And at <hi>Stoke</hi> neere <hi>Newarke</hi> was fought a great Battell by <hi>Iohn de la Poole</hi> in the reigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seuenth. This County hath 5 Riuers interfluent to water and fertilize it, of which <hi>Trent</hi> is the greateſt. It hath alſo 17 Bridges, and 18 Parkes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:44"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Nottinghamshire</figDesc>
                     <head>NOTINGHAM SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Yorkshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:45"/>
               <head>Yorke-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is the greateſt County in all this Land, and by the <hi>Saxons</hi> was called <hi>Effroc-ſcyre,</hi> and <hi>Eboraſcyre,</hi> but now by vs <hi>Yorke-ſhire,</hi> which is bounded on the Eaſt with the German Seas, on the Weſt with the Counties of <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merland</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> on the South with <hi>Cheſhire, Darby, Not ingham,</hi> and <hi>Lincolne ſhires;</hi> and on the North it is parted by the Riuer <hi>Tees</hi> from the Biſhopricke of <hi>Durham.</hi> In length (from <hi>Harthill</hi> in the South to the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Tees</hi> in the North) is contained about 70 miles, and the bredth (from <hi>Flamborough</hi> head to <hi>Horne</hi> Caſtle on the Riuer <hi>Lun</hi>) 80, making the whole compaſſe much vpon 308 miles. It is diuided into three parts, called <hi>Ridings,</hi> viz. the <hi>Eaſt, Weſt,</hi> and <hi>North Ridings;</hi> and they are ſubdiuided into Hundreds, whereof the <hi>Weſt Riding</hi> containes ten, the <hi>North Riding</hi> twelue, and the <hi>Eaſt Riding</hi> fiue, making in all 27 Hundreds, which containe in them 563 Pariſh-Churches, beſides very many Chapels of eaſe. It is interlaced with 36 Riuers, ouer which a man may paſſe by 62 Bridges. It hath but one Citie, and one Biſhops Sea, but is delighted with foure Chaſes, eight Foreſts, and 72 Parkes. It hath beene fortified with fifteene ſtrong Caſtles, and for traffique and commerce amongſt the Inhabitants is traded with 45 Market Townes, whereof the moſt famous is the ancient and renowmed Citie of <hi>Yorke,</hi> which by <hi>Ptolemy</hi> was called <hi>Brigantium,</hi> and by the <hi>Britaines Caer Effrock.</hi> It is accounted the ſecond Citie of <hi>England,</hi> and for beautie of building, and other ornaments, it farre ſurpaſſeth all others in the County. It is large, faire, rich, and populous, being made a Metropolitan Citie by <hi>Honorius,</hi> where King <hi>Henry</hi> the Ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hth eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed a Counſell, conſiſting of a Lord Preſident, with diuers Counſellors at the Kings pleaſure, and a Secretary to heare and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all cauſes in thoſe Northerne parts. In this Citie both liued and died the Emperour <hi>Seuerus,</hi> whoſe aſhes were afterwards car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Rome,</hi> and there ſhriued. Here alſo (we reade) was ſometime ſeated a Temple dedicated to the Goddeſſe <hi>Bellona.</hi> And here died the Emperour <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Chlorus,</hi> who in this citie kept his royall Court. It was moſt famous alſo for a long time, in the Engliſh <hi>Saxons</hi> time, till the <hi>Danes</hi> ſuppreſſed and deſtroyed it, yet afterwards it recouered it ſelfe, and by the Citizens was ſtrengthened with a Wall, adorned and fortified with Towers and Bulwarkes, and is now gouerned by a Lord Maior, 12. Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, diuers Chamberlaines, and a Recorder. The latitude being here 54. 3. and the longitude 23. 48. Diuers other faire, famous, and remarkable Townes are ſeated in this Prouince, as <hi>Richmond, Hul, Halifax,</hi> and many others, whereof I am abridged particularly to diſcourſe, by the ſtraightneſſe of my limits: As alſo am I reſtrained from relating of many ſtrange ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ities, wherewith this County is plentifully ſtored; as the dropping Well at <hi>Knauſbrough,</hi> the <hi>Giggleſwicke</hi> ſprings, Saint <hi>Wilfrids</hi> Needle, <hi>Conſtantius</hi> his Lamp, the Mountaine <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les,</hi> and Sea-fiſh ſtones; as alſo thoſe at <hi>Whitby,</hi> which are formed like wreathed Serpents; of all which I muſt referre you to our former and moſt famous Hiſtoriographers, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Camden,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Speed,</hi> and others. With very many Abbies, Monaſteries, and Religious houſes, hath this Shire beene adorned, which are now ſubuerted and vtterly decaied. The Aire here, though it be more ſharp and frigid than in other parts of the land, yet is it very healthfull; and the Soile, though in ſome places ſterile and barren, yet in others, fat, rich and fruitfull; ſo as what is defectiue in one part, is ſupplied by another, the whole Continent feeling no want, becauſe it is generally ſufficiently ſtored with Corne, Cattell, Fiſh, Fowle, and hath many mines of Copper, Lead, Cole, Stone. Allome, Coperaſſe, and other rich commodities.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:45"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Yorkshire</figDesc>
                     <head>YORKE SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Durham" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:46"/>
               <head>The Biſhopricke of Durham.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Prouince, which wee call <hi>The Biſhopricke of Durham,</hi> is confined on the Eaſt by the German Seas, and on the Weſt is parted from <hi>Cumberland, Weſtmoreland,</hi> and <hi>Staineſmore,</hi> by the Riuer <hi>Tees: Yorke-ſhire</hi> bounds it on the South, and <hi>Northumberland</hi> on the North. It is ſhaped in the faſhion of an Hoſcedes Triangle, hauing two ſides containing much vpon thirty miles a peece, and that by the Sea ſide but about 23 or 24, making the whole cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference to containe neere to 103 miles, within which compaſſe are diſperſed 118 Pariſh-Churches. In this Shire are interfluent eleuen Riuers, which are paſſable by twenty Bridges: and becauſe the quantitie of the County is but ſmall, there is in it but one Citie, one Biſhopricke, and but ſix Market Townes, whereof the chiefeſt is the ancient Citie of <hi>Durham,</hi> which was called by the <hi>Saxons Dun-holm,</hi> of the word <hi>Dun</hi> ſignifying an Hill, and <hi>Holme</hi> an Iland; for indeed it is almoſt circularly ingirt with the Riuer of <hi>Were.</hi> It was at firſt erected (as wee haue it by tradition) by the Monkes of <hi>Lyndisferne,</hi> who by Oracle were commanded to doe it. And here did <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour vpon an high hill raiſe a ſtrong and ſtately Caſtle; and not only ſo, but made it a County Palatine, whereof the Biſhops in times paſt haue had the Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Princes. And here was the Tombe of <hi>S. Cuthbert,</hi> whereto King <hi>Egfrid, Aelfrid, Athelſtane,</hi> and others of our Engliſh Kings, came in Pilgrimage (and ſome of them bare-footed) in humble deuotion, and to giue great gifts and offerings to the Church, in the Weſt part whereof is ſtill remaining the Marble monument of the Reuerend <hi>Beda,</hi> that learned Monke of <hi>Wermouth.</hi> And here is the Pole eleuated 54. 56. ½. and the Longitude 22. 54. The Inhabitants of this County in <hi>Ptolemies</hi> time, were the <hi>Brigantes,</hi> whom the <hi>Romans</hi> conquered, and after that, by the <hi>Saxons</hi> was this Shire made a part of the Kingdome of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> which the <hi>Danes</hi> ſubdued, and was laſtly ouercome and poſſeſſed by the <hi>Normans.</hi> About a mile from <hi>Darlington</hi> in this County, haue I ſeene 3 round Ponds of water, which the Countrey people call <hi>Hell-Kettles,</hi> which are in forme circular, the water alwayes temperately warme, and (as they ſay) neuer ſeene to be frozen. They likewiſe affirme them to be bottomeleſſe, becauſe by no meanes they could euer be ſounded. But of their ſtrange beginning, with other particulars of them, as alſo of the ſalt ſtones in the Riuer <hi>Weere</hi> at <hi>Batterby</hi> (conſidering the ſtrictneſſe of my bounds) I muſt referre you to the learned Workes of our euer famous Antiquarie <hi>M. Camden.</hi> With diuers rich Religious Houſes hath this County beene beautified, which are now defaced and ſubuerted; and with ſeuen ſtrong Caſtles was it fortified, <hi>ſed tempus edax rerum.</hi> The Aire is here ſharpe, ſubtile, and healthfull; and Soile on the Eaſt ſide well ſtored with Paſtures and Arable Grounds, but mooriſh on the South: and though other parts be more barren, yet are they ſo well ſtored with Cole-pits, that beſides their owne abundant expence, they vent ſo much to other parts, as is a conſtant annuall and exceeding great benefit to the Inhabitants.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:46"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Durham</figDesc>
                     <head>THE BISH<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>OPRICK OF DVRHAM.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Northumberland" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:47"/>
               <head>Northumberland.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His County was called by the <hi>Engliſh Saxons North-Humberland,</hi> and is bounded on the South with the Biſhopricke of <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rham,</hi> on the North with <hi>Scotland,</hi> on the Weſt with part of <hi>Scotland</hi> and part of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mberland,</hi> and on the Eaſt with the German Sea. It is faſhioned in a triangular forme, containing from the South-Eaſt to the South-weſt, about 40 miles; and from the South-weſt to the North point, much vpon 60 miles; from whence to <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llinton</hi> by the Sea Coaſt, 45 miles; whereby the whole circumference amounts to the meaſure of 145 miles or thereabouts. In which circuit are included but 46 Pariſh-Churches. Many Riuers, ouer which a man may paſſe by 16 Bridges. It hath one Foreſt in it, and eight Parkes. And for trade and traffique amongſt the Inhabitants, there are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed in this County but fiue Market Townes, whereof the principall is <hi>Nowcaſtle vpon Tine,</hi> ſo called of a new Caſtle built there by <hi>Robert</hi> the ſonne of <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour: but before the Conqueſt it was called <hi>Monke-Cheſter,</hi> as a ſtrong defence for Monkes that it ſeemes were reſident there. It is now rich and famous, and very populous by reaſon of the plentifull vent of Sea-Coles, which from thence are vttered in f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rre more abundance th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n from any other part or place in <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gland</hi> beſides. <hi>Richard</hi> the Second granted, that a Sword ſhould be carried before the Maior; and <hi>Hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> the Sixth made it a Country within it ſelfe. It hath a ſtrong wall, with eight G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes for entrance about it, and halfe ſo many Churches within it. And from thence, or rather from <hi>Ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th,</hi> beginneth that famous wall called <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Picts wall,</hi> built firſt of earth, but afterwards of ſtone by the <hi>Romans,</hi> containing (as <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a</hi> ſaith) eight foot in breadth, and twelue foot in height, reaching in length from the German Seas Eaſt to the Iriſh Seas Weſt, cutting thorow the County of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> as well as this Prouince. Another chiefe Towne here is <hi>Barw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cke,</hi> the furtheſt and ſtrongeſt of all this Land of <hi>England.</hi> It is ſituate on the Sea ſide, and on the North of the Riuer <hi>Tweede,</hi> betweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and hath many times beene toſſed by Fortune, ſometimes to the ſubiection of the <hi>Scots,</hi> and then againe to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> till <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourths time, who with his Succeſſors from time to time ſo fortified it, as it hath euer ſince remained in the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> The Pole being there eleuated 55. 51. 1/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and the Longitude 23. 0. In <hi>Ptolemies</hi> time the <hi>Ottadini</hi> were the Inhabitants of this County, which then were, ſince haue beene, and ſtill are a ſtout, hardly, and warlike people, being very excellent Light Horſe-men, as they haue often tried themſelues in their many Battells and Encounters betweene them and the <hi>Scots.</hi> Very many remarkable and nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Roman Antiquities, as old decayed Altars, Inſcriptions, Coynes, &amp;c. haue beene and yet are found as well along the Wall, as in other places of this County. The Aire here, as well as in other Northerne parts, is ſharpe, cold, and piercing; The Soile ſterile and barren, except in thoſe places next the Sea, and on the bankes of the Riuer <hi>Tyne.</hi> Their chiefeſt commoditie being Sea-Cole, wherewith they not only profit and pleaſure themſelues, but doe the like to others abundantly, by tranſporting them to other remote places.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:47"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Northumberland</figDesc>
                     <head>NORTHVMBER LAND</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Cumberland" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:48"/>
               <head>Cumberland.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His County of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> which is ſituate in the North-weſt part of this Realme, and is the furtheſt part of the Land on that point, was named <hi>Cumber</hi> of thoſe <hi>Britaines</hi> that called themſelues <hi>Cumbri</hi> and <hi>Canbri.</hi> It is borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon on the North ſide with <hi>Northumberland</hi> and part of <hi>Scotland,</hi> on the South with part of <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> on the Eaſt with <hi>Weſtmorland,</hi> and on the Weſt with the Iriſh Sea. It is long and narrow, containing in length 54 miles, and at the broadeſt is not much aboue 30. And though (as other Shires bordering on <hi>Scotland</hi> are) it is exempted from Subſidie, and therefore wants the diuiſion of Hundreds, yet are there (beſides Chapels of eaſe) 58 Pariſh-Churches contained in it: and alſo there are 20 Riuers in it, hauing 33 Bridges. There is one Citie, one Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, three Foreſts, and eight Parkes. And for traffique and commerce amongſt men, there are diſperſed in it nine Market Townes, whereof the ancient Citie of <hi>Carlile</hi> is the principall, which by the <hi>Romans</hi> was called <hi>Luguuallum,</hi> by <hi>Ptolemie Leucoipibia,</hi> and by <hi>Ninius Caer-Lualid.</hi> It is ſituate very commodiouſly and delectably, betweene the Riuers of <hi>Eden, Petterell,</hi> and <hi>Cand.</hi> It was ſtrong, faire and famous, in the time of the <hi>Romans,</hi> but was ruinated by the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Picts</hi> after their departure, till <hi>Northumberlands</hi> King <hi>Egſrid</hi> reedified and incloſed it in a wall. And afterwards, when againe the <hi>Danes</hi> had deſtroyed it, King <hi>William Ruſus</hi> built the Caſtle and reſtored it, ſo as now (beſides the naturall helps of the Riuers which encompaſſe three parts of it) it is fortified with a ſtrong ſtone wall, a Caſtle, and a Citadell, betweene which almoſt in the midſt ſtands the Cathedrall Church. The Eleuation of the Pole being there 55. 18. and the Longitude 21. 41. In <hi>Ptolemies</hi> time the <hi>Brigantes</hi> were the ancient Inhabitants of this County, but afterwards thoſe <hi>Britaines</hi> that were called <hi>Cumbri</hi> poſſeſſed it. And when the <hi>Danes</hi> had ſore troubled the <hi>Saxons,</hi> this County of <hi>Cumberland</hi> was accounted a Kingdome of it ſelfe, which King <hi>Stephen</hi> (in his time) gaue to the King of <hi>Scots;</hi> but <hi>Henry</hi> the Second both claimed and got it againe from that Crowne. In this Shire there haue beene and ſtill are found many Antiquities of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> whoſe furtheſt bounds are accounted no further than this County, as witneſſeth the tract of that admirable wall called <hi>The Picts wall,</hi> which was built by <hi>Seuerus,</hi> and whereof diuers parts doe yet remaine, where (as alſo in diuers other places) are ſtill remaining the ruines of Altars, and Inſcriptions of ſeuerall Colonies and Captaines, &amp;c. At <hi>Salkelds</hi> in this County are 77 ſtones, containing ten foot in height aboue ground, and one of them fifteene, which a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e commonly called <hi>Long Megg and her Daughters,</hi> but were erected there for the memoriall of a victorie there obtained. This Prouince as it hath beene ſtrengthned with 25 ſtrong Caſtles, ſo hath it beene beautified with many faire Religious Houſes, which by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth were vtterly ſuppreſſed. The Aire (though bitter and ſharpe) is yet healthfull. The South part of the County is hillie; the midſt leuell, and more populous, and yeeldeth ſufficient prouiſion for the Inhabitants; but the North is hillie, wilde and deſolate. The commodities here are Corne, Graſſe, Sheepe, Cattell, Fiſh, and Fowle, with blacke Lead and mines of Copper, which yeeld much profit to the Country.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:48"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Cumberland</figDesc>
                     <head>CVMBER LAND</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Westmorland" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:49"/>
               <head>Weſtmorland.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His County, called in Latine <hi>Weſtmorlandia,</hi> and <hi>Weſtmaria,</hi> we in Engliſh call <hi>Weſtmorland,</hi> for the ſtore of Moores and Hills contained in it. It is bordered vpon on the Eaſt ſide by <hi>Yorke-ſhire</hi> and <hi>The Biſhopricke of Durham,</hi> on the Weſt and North ſides with the County of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> on the South. It extendeth from <hi>Kirkland</hi> North to <hi>Burton</hi> South, 30 miles, and ſtretcheth in wideneſſe (from <hi>Eden</hi> Eaſt to <hi>Dunbalraſe</hi> ſtones in the Weſt) 24 miles, making the meaſure of the whole circuit much vpon 112 miles; in which compaſſe are contained 26 Pariſh-Churches. This Shire is well watered with eight Riuers, which haue fifteene Bridges ouer them. And in it alſo are two Foreſts, and nineteene Parks. And for intercourſe of people for commerce and traffique, there are but foure Market Townes, whereof that of the greateſt account is <hi>Kendale,</hi> which is alſo called <hi>Kirkby Kendale,</hi> being ſituate on the Riuer <hi>Can,</hi> and for that cauſe ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. It is famous for the making of woollen clothes, whereby it is become very populous and very wealthy, hauing good vtterance for them thorow all the other parts of this Land. It is ciuilly and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly gouerned by an Alderman annually elected out of his twelue brethren, which are his Aſsiſtants, and are knowne from others by their Purple Habits; with whom is ioyned a Recorder, and two Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaines. The Pole is here eleuated 54. 40. and the Longitude 21. 53. The <hi>Brigantes</hi> were alſo the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Inhabitants of this County, where at a place called <hi>Apleby</hi> are often found peeces of antique Coyne, and ſome Inſcriptions ſhewing that the <hi>Aurelian Maures</hi> kept there a ſtation in the time of the <hi>Romans.</hi> The Records of this County ſpeake but of one Monaſterie founded in it, which was built by <hi>Thomas</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Goſpatrick,</hi> neere to the Riuer <hi>Loder,</hi> where is a Spring that diuers times a day both ebbes and flowes. And there are alſo a row of ſtones ſet equidiſtant, reaching a mile in faſhion of Piramides, wherof ſome of them are nine, and ſome thirteene or fourteene foot high, which are ſuppoſed to be the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable monument of ſome notable act performed in that place. In the Riuer <hi>Can</hi> neere <hi>Kendale</hi> are two ſuch violent Water-falls, where in the deſcent it makes ſuch a noiſe, that the Inhabitants adioyning can thereby fore-iudge of the weather; for if that which is North from them ſound cleare and loud, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect faire weather: but if that on the South doe ſo, they then looke for and finde the contrary. The Aire is cold and ſharpe but very healthfull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; and the Soile alſo but barren and vnfruitfull. Their chiefeſt commodities conſiſt vpon Cloathing.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:49"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Westmorland</figDesc>
                     <head>WESTMOR LAND</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Lancashire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:50"/>
               <head>Lancaſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His in the <hi>Saxon</hi> language was called <hi>Loncaſderſcyre,</hi> which we call <hi>Lanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>The County Palatine of Lancaſter.</hi> It is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Darby-ſhire,</hi> on the Weſt with the Iriſh Seas: <hi>Cheſhire</hi> confines it on the South, and <hi>Weſtmorland, Camberland,</hi> and <hi>Yorke-ſhire,</hi> border on the North. The full length of it is (from <hi>Hallwood</hi> South to <hi>Brathey</hi> North) 57 miles, and the wideneſſe (betweene <hi>Denton</hi> Eaſt and <hi>Formby</hi> neere <hi>Altmouth</hi> Weſt) 31 miles, making the meaſure of the whole compaſſe to containe about 170 miles. The diuiſion is into ſix Hundreds, containing (beſides many Chapels of eaſe) 36 Pariſhes, ſo large and populous, as the like are not in any other part of the Land. In this County are interſperſed 33 Riuers, where ouer a man may paſſe by 24 Bridges: and one Chaſe, and 30 Parkes. And for concourſe of people for trade and traffique, in this Shire are ſeated fifteene faire Market Townes, whereof that of greateſt account is the Shire-Towne <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> which is moſt pleaſantly ſituate on the South ſide of the Riuer <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> and is adorned with a faire Church, a ſtrong Caſtle, and a ſtately Bridge. Ciuilly and orderly doth a Maior, yeerely choſen out of twelue of his Brethren, with the aſsiſtance of two Bail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffes, 24 Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes, two Chamberlaines, and a Recorder, gouerne this Towne; where the Eleuation of the Pole is 54. 18. and the Longitude 21. 36. The ancient Inhabitants of this County were alſo the <hi>Brigantes,</hi> of whom I haue ſpoken in other former Shires, and whom the Emperour <hi>Claudius</hi> ſubiugated to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans:</hi> But afterwards was this County made part of <hi>Northumberlands</hi> Kingdome, till the <hi>Danes</hi> (and after them the <hi>Normans</hi>) conquered it. In this Shire <hi>Mancheſter</hi> is notable for the Church, Colledge, and Market-place: And <hi>Riblecheſter</hi> (ſometimes the ſeat of the <hi>Romans</hi>) for that it was once held to be the richeſt Towne in all Chriſtendome. Here alſo neere <hi>Furneſſe Fills</hi> is <hi>Wynander-mere,</hi> being very deepe, and ten miles in length, accounted for the greateſt ſtanding water in all this Land, and yet is all paued with ſtone in the bottome. This County is alſo famous for the foure <hi>Henries,</hi> viz. the Fourth, Fifth, Sixth, and Seuenth, which deſcending from <hi>Iohn of Gaunt,</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> were all afterwards renowmed Kings of <hi>England.</hi> Diuers Caſtles, and foure Religious Houſes, are now ſuppreſſed, that ſometimes adorned this County. The Aire is here healthfull, though cold and ſearching; And the Soile, though not ſo fertile as in other places, yet produceth large Cattell, good Corne, with Graſſe, Ilax, Cole, and almoſt all other neceſſary commodities.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:50"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Lancashire</figDesc>
                     <head>LANCASHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Cheshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:51"/>
               <head>Cheſ-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Shire, which we call the County Palatine of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> was by the <hi>Saxons</hi> both called and written <hi>Ceſtenſcire,</hi> and is diuided from <hi>Darby</hi> &amp; <hi>Stafford-ſhires</hi> on the Eaſt, by the Riuers of <hi>Goit, Dane,</hi> and <hi>Mercey;</hi> and on the Weſt, by <hi>Dee,</hi> from <hi>Denbygh.</hi> On the Northſide lies <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſhire,</hi> and the South is confined with <hi>Flint</hi> and <hi>Shrop-ſhire.</hi> It containeth in length from Eaſt to Weſt 47. miles, and at the broadeſt betweene North and South 26. which cauſeth the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the whole circumference to contain about 142. miles. This County is diuided into 7. Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreds, which containe in them (beſides 38. Chapels of eaſe) 86. Pariſh Churches. It hath alſo in it one Citie, one Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, and is watered with 9. Riuers, ouer which men doe paſſe by 19. Bridges. Two Foreſts and 18. Parkes are alſo in this Shire. And for traffique and commerce amongſt the Inhabitants, there are diſperſed in conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient places 15. Market Townes, the chiefe whereof is the faire and famous Citie of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> of which the whole Countie carries the name, and was ſometimes the ſtrong Fort of <hi>Ostorius,</hi> who was <hi>Claudius</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Lieu-tenant. It is pleaſantly ſituate on the North ſide of the Riuer <hi>Dee,</hi> ouer which a faire and ſtrong ſtone Bridge, built on 8. arches and beautified: two faire gates at each end: giue paſſage to the Towne, which is incircled with a high and ſtrong wall, containing (beſides ſeuen Towers and three Poſternes) foure faire Gates at the foure Cardinall points of the Compaſſe. On the North ſide of this Citie, Earle <hi>Leofrick</hi> built the Minſter, which by <hi>Hugh</hi> the firſt <hi>Normaine</hi> Earle of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> was afterward both repaired and fairely beautified. And in it (as we haue it by tradition) <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, Emperour of <hi>Almane,</hi> after he had there a long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime led a Hermits life, was interred: and on the South ſide ſtands the Caſtle, incompaſſed with a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular wall. This Citie was firſt ruined by the <hi>Northumberland</hi> King <hi>Egfrid,</hi> who there ſlew 1200. Monkes, and afterwards by the <hi>Danes,</hi> but by <hi>Edelſteda</hi> was both reedified and beautified. In this Citie King <hi>Edgar</hi> was towed from Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> to his Palace by eight other Kings, who did him homage, and himſelfe as Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme ſteered the Helme. And <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth made it a Countie of it ſelfe, which is now gouerned by an annually elected Maior, two Sheriffes, foure and twenty Aldermen, and a Recorder. It hath had in it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Religious houſes, which time hath now transformed to ruines. The Pole is there eleuated 53. 15. of Latitude, and the Longitude 21. 27. This Shire hath beene fortified with eight other Caſtles, and as many famous Religious Houſes, which were ſuppreſſed by King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight. The Aire in this Countie is both pleaſant and healthfull; the Soile fat, rich and fruitfull, bringing abundance both of profit and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to the Inhabitants. And for Commodities, it yeelds plentifull ſtore of Corne, Cattell, Fowle, Fiſh, Salt, Mines, Metalls, White-meats, and moſt of all other neceſſary and vſefull commodities.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:51"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Cheshire</figDesc>
                     <head>CHESSHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Shropshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:52"/>
               <head>Shropſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Shire by the old <hi>Saxons</hi> was written and termed <hi>Sciripſcyre,</hi> which at this day we call <hi>Shropſhire.</hi> It is bordered vpon on the Eaſt with <hi>Stafford-ſhire,</hi> on the Weſt with <hi>Denbigh</hi> and <hi>Montgomery: Radnor, Hereford,</hi> and <hi>Worceſter-ſhires</hi> doe bound vpon the South, and the County Palatine of <hi>Cheſter</hi> on the North. From <hi>Wooferton</hi> South, to <hi>Ouer</hi> neere <hi>Trent</hi> on the North, (which is the full length) it containes 34 miles, and at the broadeſt (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Tong</hi> in the Eaſt and <hi>Oſweſtre</hi> Weſt) 25, making the whole circumference to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine about 134 miles. The diuiſion of this County is ſhared into 15 Hundreds, whoſe ſubdiuiſion into Pariſhes is 170. It is well watered with 18 Riuers, which haue 13 large Bridges for paſſage. And in this Shire are found 7 Foreſts, and 27 Parks. In 14 Market Townes haue the Inhabitants commerce and traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique, wherof that of moſt note is the ancient Shire-Towne of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> which is both large and weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, containing many faire Streets, adorned with beautifull buildings, wherein are many rich and weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Inhabitants, who honeſtly attaine thereto, by their trading for the moſt part in Wools, Cloth, and Freeſe. It is ſtrongly walled, hauing a Bulwarke deſcending from the Caſtle to the ſide of <hi>Seuerre,</hi> on the North banke whereof is the Towne moſt pleaſantly ſituate: and for paſſage, on the Eaſt and Weſt ſides are built two faire Bridges of ſtone, and another entrance on the North, ouer which ſtands the ruinous remainder of the old Caſtle. The gouernment of this Towne is committed to two annually elected Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffes, with 24 Burgeſſes, and a Recorder. The height of the Pole is here 52. 49. and the Longitude 21. 38. This County in times paſt hath beene much troubled with many grieuous broiles, which cauſed the Inhabitants to fortifie themſelues with diuers walled Townes, and 32 ſtrong Caſtles, whereof now moſt of them are vtterly decayed, but that at <hi>Ludlow</hi> was made by King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seuenth the Court of his eldeſt Palace for the Lord Preſident, who with diuers Counſellors, a Secretary, Atturney, Sollicitor, and foure Iuſtices of the <hi>Welch</hi> Counties, he appointed in their Termes to plead, heare, and determine of cauſes. Neere <hi>Clune</hi> Caſtle in this Shire is yet remaining the Fort of <hi>Cara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> a Prince of the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lures,</hi> about the yeere of our Lord 53, which was won by <hi>P. Oſtorius</hi> the <hi>Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> In which Towne of <hi>Clune,</hi> amongſt other memorable paſſages, I ſaw a Pardon for one <hi>Iohn Clune</hi> Eſquire, ſeruant to King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, for reſeruation of his name and bloud, who accidentally ſlew one of the Burgeſſes thereof in the Church-yard: which Pardon was granted and ſigned by Pope <hi>Iulian</hi> the ſecond, and was ſhewed to mee by m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good friend Maſter <hi>Edmund Clun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Maurice Clun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> of the ſame Houſe and Familie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eally deſcending. The A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re in this County is both healthfull and pleaſant; the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le rich and fertile, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lding Wheat, Barly, Pit-cole, Iron, and Woods in abundance.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:52"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Shropshire</figDesc>
                     <head>SHROPSHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Herefordshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:53"/>
               <head>Hereford-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His County (which wee call <hi>Hereford-ſhire</hi>) was named by the <hi>Britaines Ereinuc.</hi> It is bordered vpon on the North with <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>Shropſhires,</hi> on the South with <hi>Monmouth-ſhire;</hi> on the Eaſt it is diuided from <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire</hi> by <hi>Maluerne Hills,</hi> and the Weſt is bounded by <hi>Brecknock</hi> and <hi>Radnor-ſhires.</hi> The forme of it is circular, containing in length (from <hi>Maluerne Hills</hi> on the Eaſt, to <hi>Michael Church</hi> Weſt) about 26 miles; and in bredth (from <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruthell</hi> South to <hi>Ouer Sapie</hi> North) 24 miles, cauſing the whole circumference to amount to 102 miles, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts. It is diuided into 11 Hundreds, and thoſe are ſubdiuided into 176 Pariſhes. It containes one Citie, one Biſhopricke, thirteene Riuers paſſable by eleuen Bridges; one Chaſe, two Foreſts, and eighteene Parks. And for commerce and trade the Inhabitants haue eight Market Townes, whereof the principall is the Citie of <hi>Hereford,</hi> which worthy <hi>M. Camden</hi> is of opinion to haue ſprung from the ruines of old <hi>Ariconium,</hi> but is delectably ſeated amongſt pleaſant Medowes and plentifull Corne-fields, and almoſt round about encircled with the Riuer of <hi>Wye,</hi> and another on the North ſide whoſe name is not knowne. It grew firſt famous for the ſuppoſed ſanctitie of King <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> who was there entombed after he had beene murthered by King <hi>Offaes</hi> wife, when he came to wooe her daughter: and in honour of him did <hi>Mildred</hi> a petty King of that County build the Cathedrall Church, which afterward was conſumed by fire, but reedified by Biſhop <hi>Reiuelin,</hi> and the Towne incloſed in a wall, with ſix Gates, and fifteene Towers: and is ciuilly gouerned by a Maior (yeerely elected out of 13. Citizens) and his Brethren, whereof foure of the ancienteſt are Iuſtices of Peace, and a Recorder. The Latitude being there 52. 7. ½. and the Longitude 21. 50. In this Citie King <hi>Athelſtane</hi> (as <hi>Malmesbury</hi> reports) cauſed the Lords of <hi>Wales</hi> to pay an annuall Tribute (beſides Hawkes and Hounds) of twenty pounds of Gold, and 300 pounds of Siluer by weight. The ancient Inhabitants of this County were the <hi>Silures,</hi> a fierce, hardy, and valiant people, as appeares by their nine yeeres oppoſition to the <hi>Romans.</hi> And afterwards the <hi>Saxons</hi> made this County a part of their <hi>Mercian</hi> Kingdome: and <hi>Sutton</hi> was their Royall Court kept of their great King <hi>Offa.</hi> Before the Conqueſt this County was accounted vvith thoſe of <hi>Wales</hi> againſt <hi>England;</hi> but when it was ioyned to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> with diuers Caſtles was it fortified againſt the <hi>Welch:</hi> for wee reade that in times paſt it hath beene ſtrengthned with 28 ſtrong and faire Caſtles, moſt of which are now low buried in the heapes of their owne ruines. Of remarkable things in this Shire, the Spring called <hi>Bone Well,</hi> neere <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards Caſtle,</hi> is famous for Fiſh-bones and no Fiſh, which though it be cleerely cleanſed thereof, will ſhortly after be furniſhed afreſh with the like. But the great wonder was the admirable motion of <hi>Marcley Hill,</hi> containing about 26 acres, within our owne memorie, <hi>Anno</hi> 1571, which with a great noiſe remoued it ſelfe from its owne place, and went continually for three dayes together, carrying with it ſheepe in their coats, hedge-rowes and trees, and ouerthrowing <hi>Kinnaſton</hi> Chapell, and diuers trees, turning two high waies neere 100 yards from their vſuall Road, and bearing the earth before it the ſpace of 400 yards. With very many Religious Houſes hath this Shire beene adorned; but in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth were vtterly ruinated, as many others in all other Counties. The Aire is here pleaſent, healthfull, and temperate; and the Soile as fertile and fruitfull as any other in <hi>England,</hi> yeelding Corne, Cattell, Wooll, Wheat, and almoſt all other neceſſary commodities, for the vſe of the Inhabitants.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:53"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Herefordshire</figDesc>
                     <head>HEREFORD SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Radnorshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:54"/>
               <head>Radnor-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Adnor-ſhire,</hi> in the <hi>Britiſh Sire Maiſeueth,</hi> being in forme threeſquare, is on the South ſide ſeparated from <hi>Brecknok-ſhire</hi> by the Riuer <hi>Wy;</hi> on the North it bordereth vpon <hi>Montgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mery-ſhire;</hi> on the South-eaſt vpon <hi>Hereford-ſhire.</hi> The Eaſt and South parts of this Shire be farre more fruitfull than the reſt. It hath in it two and fiftie Pariſhes, and three Townes of note, the principall whereof is <hi>Radnor,</hi> in <hi>Britiſh Maiſeueth,</hi> which in times paſt was firmely fenced with a wall, but after that <hi>Owen Glendowre</hi> had burnt it, it began to grow to decay. It is probable that this <hi>Maiſeueth</hi> or <hi>Radnor,</hi> was that ancient Citie <hi>Magi,</hi> which <hi>Antonine</hi> the Emperour calleth <hi>Magnos,</hi> where the Gouernour of the <hi>Pacenſian</hi> Regiment lay in garriſon vnder the Lieu-tenant of <hi>Britaine,</hi> in the reigne of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the younger: for Writers of the middle age call the Inhabitants of this coaſt <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſetae,</hi> and make mention of Earles <hi>Mageſetenſes;</hi> alſo the diſtance, if it be counted from <hi>Gobannium</hi> or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergeuenny,</hi> or from <hi>Brangonium,</hi> (i.) <hi>Worceſter</hi> differeth not from <hi>Antonines</hi> computation. Three miles Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from this Towne lieth <hi>Preſtaine,</hi> in <hi>Britiſh Lhan Andrew</hi> (i.) S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Andrews</hi> Church, which of a very little Village, by the meanes of <hi>Richard Martin,</hi> Biſhop of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Davids,</hi> is of late yeares growne to be ſo great and faire a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rket Towne, that it dimmeth the light of <hi>Radnor.</hi> Scarce foure miles from <hi>Preſtaine</hi> ſtandeth <hi>Knigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> a Towne not inferiour to the former, it is called in the <hi>Britiſh Trebuclo,</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Trefyclaudh,</hi> of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Ditch lying vnder it, which <hi>Offa,</hi> King of the <hi>Mercians,</hi> cauſed to be caſt from <hi>Dee</hi> mouth to <hi>Wye</hi> mouth, to ſeparate the <hi>Britaines</hi> from his <hi>Engliſh-men.</hi> In the South-weſt of this Countrey lieth a wide wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, into which <hi>Vortigerne</hi> (whoſe memory the <hi>Britaines</hi> may wiſh damned) withdrew himſelfe, when he had called the <hi>Saxons</hi> into this Land, and in horrible inceſt married his owne daughter; and here was he, with his Citie <hi>Treguortig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rn,</hi> burnt with fire from heauen. And not farre from the place where this <hi>Vor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> the laſt abſolute Monarch of the <hi>Britaines,</hi> periſhed, was <hi>Lhewellin,</hi> the laſt Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> of the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> race, ſlaine by <hi>Roger Francton.</hi> The <hi>Mortimers,</hi> not long after the Conqueſt, wonne a great part of this little countrey, and after that they had beene a long time eminent aboue others in theſe parts, King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third created <hi>Roger Mortimer,</hi> Lord of <hi>Wigmore,</hi> Earle of theſe <hi>Welſh</hi> limits, or according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſpeech, Earle of <hi>March.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:54"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Radnorshire</figDesc>
                     <head>RADNOR SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Brecknockshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:55"/>
               <head>Brecknock-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Countie of <hi>Brecknock</hi> was called <hi>Brechineau</hi> in the <hi>Britiſh tongue,</hi> of one <hi>Brichauius,</hi> a Prince, that as the Inhabitants report, had foure and twentie daughters, and all of them Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized for Saints. It is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Monmouth</hi> and <hi>Radnor-ſhires:</hi> on the Weſt with <hi>Carmarden</hi> and <hi>Cardigan:</hi> on the South with <hi>Glamorgan;</hi> and the North ſide by the Riuers <hi>Wye</hi> and <hi>Clarwen,</hi> is diuided from <hi>Radnor.</hi> The length of it from <hi>Istragunles</hi> South, to <hi>Llanuthel</hi> North is 28. miles, and the extent of the broadeſt part from <hi>Pentriſſo</hi> Eaſt, to <hi>Llywell</hi> Weſt 20. the whole compaſſe containing much vpon 102. miles. Into ſix Hundreds is this Shire ſevered, and thoſe are ſubdiuided into 61. Pariſhes: with 27. Riuers is it interlaced, ouer which in diuers places are 13. Bridges for paſſage. And for Traffique and trade amongſt the Inhabitants, it is ſtored but with three Market Townes, namely, <hi>Hay, Bealt,</hi> and the Shire Towne <hi>Brecknock,</hi> which is now accounted the principall, though the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two in former times would haue beene preferred. <hi>Hay,</hi> pleaſantly ſeated on <hi>Wye</hi> and <hi>Dulas,</hi> in <hi>Owen Glen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowrs</hi> rebellion was vtterly ruinated; and <hi>Bealt,</hi> though ſtill in ſome frequencie, yet is now nothing to what in antique Ages it hath beene; but <hi>Brecknock</hi> at this time is the beſt, which being pleaſantly ſeated on the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers <hi>Vske</hi> and <hi>Howthy,</hi> is fortified with a faire ſtrong wall, that beſides ten Towers, hath 3. Gates for entrance, with a ſtately Caſtle, ſituate on the Weſt part of the Towne, and is moreouer beautified with diuers faire buildings. It is ciuilly gouerned by two Bayliffes, fifteene Aldermen, two Chamberlaines, two Conſtables; where the Pole is eleuated. 52. 8. and the longitude 21. 11. The Inhabitants of this Countie, that anciently poſſeſſed it, were the <hi>Silures,</hi> who greatly oppoſed the <hi>Romans,</hi> whereto they were much aduantaged by the huge Mountaines, wherewith the Shire is repleniſhed; one of them neere <hi>Brecknock,</hi> which in <hi>Welſh</hi> they call <hi>Mounch-denny,</hi> is of an vncredible height, in ſo much as nothing, without it be ſome metalline ſubſtance or ſtone, can be caſt from the top of it, but with the aire and wind it will be blowne vp again, and neuer fall to the ground. <hi>Llynſauathan</hi> alſo, which is neare to <hi>Brecknock,</hi> is alſo admirable, for there (by report) ſtood a ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Citie, which ſuncke downe in an earthquake. And with nine Caſtles hath this Countie beene accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated. The Aire being cold, ſharpe, and piercing; and the Soile though for the moſt part hilly, ſterill and barren, yet the freſh Riuerers iſſuing from the Mountaines, make the Valleyes ſo fruitfull, as they yeeld both Corne and Graſſe in abundance.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:55"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Brecknockshire</figDesc>
                     <head>BRECKNOCK SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Monmouthshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:56"/>
               <head>Monmouth-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the Riuer <hi>Mounowe</hi> is this Towne <hi>Monmouth</hi> ſo termed, and from that Towne we call this Countie <hi>Monmouth-ſhire:</hi> which on the Eaſt is bordered vpon by <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire,</hi> on the Weſt by <hi>Brecknock</hi> and <hi>Glamorgan-ſhires.</hi> The South is bounded by the <hi>Seuerne</hi> Sea, and the North by the Riuer <hi>Monnowe,</hi> diuided from <hi>Hereford-ſhire.</hi> The extent of the greateſt meaſure between North and South, is about twenty foure miles in length, and at the wideſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Eaſt and Weſt, not aboue nineteen, the whole circumference being much vpon 76. miles. The diuiſion of it is into ſix Hundreds, wherein are contained 127. Pariſh Churches, and with the pleaſant ſtreames of fifteene Riuers, paſſable by fourteene Bridges is it interlaced; beſides which, for more delight in this Shire is there one Chace and eight Parks: and for Trade and Traffique of buying and ſelling, ſix Market Townes, whereof that of the greateſt note, is the ancient Shire Towne of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> which betweene the two Riuers <hi>Wye</hi> and <hi>Monnowe</hi> is very delectably ſituate: wherein is yet remaining a faire Church and thirteene Gates, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Towre vpon the Bridge. But that which was called the Monkes Church, and was in times paſt moſt curiouſly edified in the Eaſt end of the Towne, is now vtterly ruined, as well as the Caſtle on the North, which yet will be euer memorable for the birth of the famous and victorious King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth. The go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of this Towne is committed to a Maior, two Bayliffes, fifteene common Councellours, and a Towne Clerke. The eleuation of the Pole being there 15. 53. and the Longitude 21. 39. The <hi>Silures</hi> were the ancient Inhabitants of this Countie, who had <hi>Caerwent</hi> for their principall place of abode, where the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Tathaie</hi> made an Academie. And at <hi>Caer-Lion</hi> lay the ſecond <hi>Romane</hi> Legion called <hi>Augusta,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of yet are found many antique <hi>Romane</hi> teſtimonies. And here alſo did the great King <hi>Arthur</hi> keepe his Royall Court, which then was a moſt magnificent Citie, but is now intombed in the heapes of her owne ruines. And ſo alſo are diuers Religious Houſes ſometime that beautified, and fourteene ſtrong Caſtles, that ſome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me fortified this famous Prouince: where the Aire is pleaſant and healthfull, and the Soile, (though hilly) yet rich, fruitfull, and full of Woods; yeelding plenty of Corne, Graſſe, Cattell, and many other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſary Commodities.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:56"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Monmouthshire</figDesc>
                     <head>MONMOUTH SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Glamorgan" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:57"/>
               <head>Glamorgan-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Province which is called <hi>Glamorgan-ſhire,</hi> is ſuppoſed by ſome to deriue the name from one <hi>Morgan,</hi> a Prince that poſſeſſed it; but others hold, that it hath it from the Abbey <hi>Morgan,</hi> which on the South ſide of this Shire, neare the Sea, did Earle <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Glocester</hi> build. And it is ſeuered by the Riuer <hi>Remner</hi> on the Eaſt, from the Countie of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> and on the Weſt, by the Riuer <hi>Loghor</hi> from <hi>Caermarden-ſhire.</hi> The South is incloſed with the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Sea, and the North is bounded vpon by <hi>Brecknock.</hi> It containes in length, from Eaſt to Weſt, almoſt forty miles, and in the breadth, from South to North, almoſt twenty, making the whole compaſſe to containe 112. miles, which are diſtinguiſhed into twelue Hundreds, and thoſe are ſubdiuided into 118. Pariſhes. This Shire is well watered with ſixteene Riuers, and containes for Commerce and Trade ſix Market Townes, whereof the chiefeſt is <hi>Cardiffe,</hi> which the <hi>Britaines</hi> called <hi>Caerdid,</hi> being pleaſantly ſituated on the Eaſt ſide of the Riuer <hi>Taue,</hi> and in King <hi>Rufus</hi> time was ſtrengthened with a wall, hauing foure Gates, and a ſtrong Caſtle built by <hi>Fitz-Haimon:</hi> but afterwards the <hi>Normans</hi> wan it, and <hi>Rufus</hi> made it his Royall Court. This Towne is Gouerned by a Maior, annually elected out of twelue Aldermen, who are aſſiſted with as many other Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes, a Towne Clerke, and foure Conſtables. The eleuation of the Pole being there 51. 32 ½. and the Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude 20. 21.. And neare to this is the Citie <hi>Landaffe,</hi> where nothing but the Cathedrall Church and Caſtle is worthy obſeruance. <hi>Minyd-Margan</hi> is a Hill in this County, on the top whereof is a Monument, that hath ſuch ſtrange Characters, that (as the countrey people report and beleeue) hee that readeth them ſhall ſhortly after die. This Countie in times paſt hath beene ſtrongly fortified with fiue and twentie Caſtles, whereof the moſt part are quite conſumed to ruines, as are alſo ſome Religious Houſes, which in former ages did adorne this Countrey. The Aire is cheerefull, pleaſant and temperate. And the Soile, though the more North, the more Hilly, yet Southward, is plaine, euen and fruitfull, yeelding to the Inhabitants good ſtore of Corne and Cattell.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:57"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Glamorgan</figDesc>
                     <head>GLAMORGAN SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Carmarthenshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:58"/>
               <head>Caermarden-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Countie of <hi>Caermarden</hi> hath the name from the Towne of <hi>Caermarden,</hi> which the ancient <hi>Britaines</hi> called <hi>Caer-Firdhin,</hi> and is inuironed on the Eaſt with <hi>Brecknock</hi> and <hi>Glamorgan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> on the Weſt with <hi>Pembrook-ſhire;</hi> on the South with the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Sea, and on the North with <hi>Cardigan-ſhire.</hi> The length of it from point to point, in the longeſt part, being not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue fiue and thirty miles, and the wideneſſe from the broadeſt part twentie, ſo as the meaſure of the whole circumference containes about an hundred and two miles. It is parted into ſix Hundreds, which are againe diuided into 87. Pariſhes. It is irriguated with eight and twenty Riuers, which may be paſſed by ſixteene Bridges: and it containeth two Parkes and foure Foreſts. In ſix Market Townes haue the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants Traffique and Commerce, the chiefe whereof is the Shire Towne <hi>Caermarden,</hi> which in <hi>Ptolomies</hi> time was called <hi>Maridunum,</hi> and is very delectably ſituate on the Weſterne ſide of the Riuer <hi>Towy,</hi> which diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the whole Shire in the middeſt: ouer which water is a faire ſtrong built Bridge of ſtone, for paſſage to the Towne; wherein vpon a Rocke is ſeated a large Caſtle, from whence a wall enuironeth the Towne, where (by report wee haue it) was borne the famous <hi>Welch</hi> Prophet <hi>Merlin,</hi> being the ſonne of an <hi>Incubus</hi> ſpirit. This Towne hath formerly bin the Exchequer for all South <hi>Wales.</hi> The gouernment wherof is now commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a Maior (who euer after is a Iuſtice of Peace) with two Sheriffes and ſixteene Burgeſſes. The Pole be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there eleuated 50. 50. &amp; the Latitude 20. 16. The ancient Inhabitants of this Countie, were the <hi>Dimetriae,</hi> yet ſome thinke they were part of the <hi>Silures,</hi> and that this Shire was afterward the ſtrong Fort of the <hi>Romans,</hi> where lay their Legions, as appeareth by their Coines lately found at <hi>Kilmanlloyd.</hi> Some ſeuen or eight mile Eaſtward from <hi>Caermarden</hi> are the ruines of Caſtle <hi>Carreg</hi> on the top of an high Hill, which is famous for ſpacious holes and wide Caues that are within it, and alſo for a Well which ebbes and flowes twice euery foure and twentie houres. The Aire is here pleaſant, temperate and healthfull. The Soile not ſo Hilly, and more fertile than in ſome adioyning Shires. And for Commodities produceth Corne, Cattell, Graſſe, Woods and Pit-coale, with plentie of Fowle and Fiſh, whereof the Salmon is there caught in very great abundance.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:58"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Carmarthenshire</figDesc>
                     <head>CARMADEN SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Pembrokeshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:59"/>
               <head>Pembroke-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Shire which (as learned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Cambden</hi> reports) was in old books named the Lawfull Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Pembroch,</hi> is bounded on the Eaſt ſide by the County of <hi>Caermarden,</hi> on the Weſt and South by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Seas, and on the North with the Riuers <hi>Keach</hi> and <hi>Tyuy</hi> is diuided from <hi>Cardigan.</hi> And the length of the Shire from <hi>Cardigan</hi> North, to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Gowers</hi> point South, containes 26. miles; and the bredth from <hi>Landeny</hi> Eaſt, to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Dauids</hi> point Weſt, about twenty; whereby the whole compaſſe is accounted much vpon 93. miles. The diuiſion of this Shire is into ſeuen Hundreds, wherein are diſperſed the number of 145. Pariſh Churches. There being interfluent in this Countie ſix Riuers, that haue ſeuen Bridges. In it alſo are two Foreſts and three Parkes: And for the Inhabitants intercourſe for Trade and Traffique, they are furniſhed in this County with ſiue Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Townes, whereof that which is accounted the chiefe, is <hi>Pembroke,</hi> the Shire Towne, and Denominator of the Countie, which is pleaſantly ſeated on the Banke of a Creeke, where the water ebbeth and floweth euen vp to the walls: which hauing three Gates in a long forme (and now decaying) doe incloſe the Towne, which on the Weſt end hath a Caſtle, that hath beene large and ſtrong. And a Cauſey locked, which is the way to <hi>Monton Priory,</hi> now ſuppreſſed. Within the walls are two Pariſh Churches, and the Towne at this day gouerned by a Maior, aſſiſted with Bayliffes and Burgeſſes: the height of the Pole being there 51. 47. and the Longitude 19. 40. Another Towne note-worthy in the Weſt of this Shire, is ancient S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Dauids,</hi> which is barren and vnfruitfull, ſtanding open to all kinde of ill weather, and yet from thence came S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi> the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Apoſtle, whoſe parents were the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Prieſt <hi>Calphurnius</hi> and his wife <hi>Concha,</hi> that was Siſter to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Martin.</hi> This Citie, though ill ſtored with houſes and Inhabitants, hath yet a faire Cathedrall Church, in the Quire whereof is intombed <hi>Edmund</hi> Earle of <hi>Richmond,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seuenths father, for whoſe ſake King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth ſpared the pulling downe of this Church in the time of Suppreſſion. The anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Inhabitants of this County were the <hi>Dimetriae,</hi> but long after King <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt planted <hi>Flemings</hi> there, <hi>Monto Priory</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Dogmells</hi> were the Religious Houſes that I finde were erected in this Shire, and in the diſſolution were ſuppreſſed; yet with ſixteene ſtrong Caſtles and two Block-houſes at the mouth of <hi>Milford</hi> Hauen was it well fortified. The Aire being temperate and wholeſome, and the Soile fat, fertile and full of Marle, yeelding plentie of Corne, Cattell, Fowle and Fiſh.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:59"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Pembrokeshire</figDesc>
                     <head>PENBROKE SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Cardiganshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:60"/>
               <head>Cardigan-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Countie of <hi>Cardigan,</hi> called by old <hi>Latine</hi> Writers <hi>Geretica,</hi> and in <hi>Britiſh, Sire-Aber-Tius,</hi> is bordered vpon on the Eaſt by <hi>Montgomery</hi> and <hi>Brecknock-ſhires,</hi> on the Weſt by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Sea, on the South by <hi>Towy</hi> and <hi>Tiuy</hi> is diuided from <hi>Caermarden-ſhire,</hi> and on the North by the Riuer <hi>Douy,</hi> from <hi>Merioneth-ſhire.</hi> It containes from <hi>Cardigan</hi> Towne in the South, to the Riuer <hi>Douy</hi> on the North, 32. miles, and ſtretcheth her wideſt part from <hi>Clarwen</hi> head in the Eaſt, to <hi>Aberyſtwyth</hi> on the Weſt, but fifteene; the whole content of the compaſſe being about 103. miles. It is diuided into fiue Hundreds, which are ſubdiuided into 64. Pariſhes: 26. Riuers and Riuerets, with nine Bridges, are pleaſantly interſperſed in it. And for negotiating of buſineſſe for the Inhabitants, foure Market Townes, whereof <hi>Cardigan</hi> the Shire Towne is the principall, which on the North ſide of the Riuer <hi>Tyuy,</hi> on a high banke is pleaſantly ſeated, which <hi>Gilbert de Clare,</hi> to whom King <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt gaue this County, encompaſſed with a wall that hath three waies for paſſage into the Towne; and built there alſo vpon a Rocke, a faire large and ſtrong Caſtle, which the bitter ſtormes of time haue now transformed into a monument of ruines: vnder which Caſtle is the Bridge, which is the onely paſſable way ouer the Riuer <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy.</hi> The eleuation of the Pole is here 52. 16. and the Longitude 19. 55. The ancient Inhabitants of this Countie, that <hi>Ptolemie</hi> makes mention of, were the <hi>Dimetiae,</hi> who vnder the conduct of their King <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ractacus,</hi> were moſt valiant oppoſers of the <hi>Romans,</hi> till <hi>Iulius Frontinus</hi> ouercame and ſubdued them. This ſmall Shire, I finde was furniſhed with few Religious Houſes, namely at <hi>Cardigan Iſtradfleet, Llan-Badern-Vaur,</hi> which ſometime was a Biſhops Sea, and yet theſe few could not eſcape the force of Fortune, and Time the deuourer of all things. The Aire is here open, ſharp, and piercing, and yet withall wholeſome. The Soile hilly and vneuen, except towards the Sea-ſide, where it is more plaine, hauing pleaſant valleyes and rich paſtures. And the chiefeſt Commodities of this Countie are Corne, Cattell, Fowle and Fiſh; and in ſome places are Mines of Lead.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:60"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Cardiganshire</figDesc>
                     <head>CARDIGAN SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Montgomeryshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:61"/>
               <head>Montgomery-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His County which we call <hi>Montgomery-ſhire,</hi> by the <hi>Britaines</hi> was called <hi>Sire-Trefald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win,</hi> and on the Eaſt is incloſed with <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> on the Weſt with <hi>Merioneth-ſhire: Radnor</hi> and <hi>Cardican-ſhires</hi> border on the South, and the North is bounded with the Countie of <hi>Denbigh.</hi> The meaſure of the length from <hi>Hyſſyngton</hi> Eaſt to <hi>Machenlett</hi> Weſt, is about 26. miles, and the broadeſt betweene the Riuers of <hi>Dulas</hi> South, and <hi>Riader</hi> North, much vpon 22. The diuiſion of it is into ſeuen Hundreds, wherein are in diuers places diſperſed 47. Pariſh Churches: and with many ſweet Riuers that have ſix Bridges for paſſage is this Countie accommodated, whereof <hi>Seuerne,</hi> the ſecond of all the Land, hath the head riſing and iſſuing from the high Hill <hi>Plymllymon,</hi> whence alſo deſcend from their heads, the Riuers of <hi>Wye</hi> and <hi>Rydall.</hi> The Inhabitants of this Countie haue for Commerce and Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique ſix Market Townes, whereof the chiefeſt is the Shire Towne <hi>Montgomery,</hi> which vpon the ſide of an hill is pleaſantly ſituated in a very healthfull Aire, neare to which vpon a higher mount is ſeated a faire and ſtrong Caſtle, that is yet kept and maintained in very good repaire, hauing a moſt pleaſant Plaine vnder it: It was built by <hi>Roger de Montgomery,</hi> Earle of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> and called by the <hi>Latins Mons Gomericus.</hi> The Pole is here eleuated 52. 43. and the Longitude 21. 17. The hardy <hi>Ordouices</hi> were the ancient Inhabitants that poſſeſſed this Countie, who were a warlike people, that valiantly a long time withſtood the <hi>Romane</hi> Forces, and held out from the ſubiection of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> till the reigne of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt; but ſince that time haue euer beene found moſt firme and faithfull to the Crowne. The Aire is here very delightfull and healthfull; The Soyle Hilly and vneuen, but plentifull of faire and freſh water Springs. The Eaſt part of this Shire being as fruitfull as any part of <hi>England,</hi> and the Weſt breeding abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſtore of Cattell, but eſpecially of excellent Horſes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:61"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Montgomeryshire</figDesc>
                     <head>MOUNTGOMERIE SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Merionethshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:62"/>
               <head>Merioneth-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Latines</hi> call this Countie <hi>Meruinia,</hi> which the <hi>Britaines</hi> termed <hi>Syre-Verioneth,</hi> and wee now call <hi>Merioneth-ſhire.</hi> Which boundeth thus: <hi>Montgomery-ſhire</hi> bordereth the Eaſt, and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Seas doe waſh upon the Weſt. <hi>Cardigan-ſhire</hi> is diuided from it by the Riuer <hi>Dowy</hi> on the South: and the North is limited by the Counties <hi>Carnarnan</hi> and <hi>Denbigh.</hi> It contains in length, from <hi>Aber-Dowy</hi> South-weſt, to <hi>Llanſansfred</hi> North-Eaſt, about 33. miles, and in bredth from <hi>Maynlloyd</hi> South-eaſt, to <hi>Bethkelert</hi> Bridge 22. It is diuided into ſix Hundreds, wherein are contained 37. Pariſh Churches, and 26. Riuers paſſable by ſeuen Bridges. And for Commerce and Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique in this Countie, are but three Market Townes, <hi>viz. Bala, Dolgelhe</hi> and <hi>Harlech,</hi> which is accounted the principall, though it be much defectiue both of building or any other ornaments befitting a Shire Towne, for in a barren place it ſtands, but bleake and cold, where there is little plentie of any thing but of Fowle and Fiſh. Yet is there a ſtrong and faire Caſtle, ſituate vpon a Mount encircled with a double Bulwarke, which is a ſure defence againſt the entrance there of any forren inuaders. And though the Conſtable of this Caſtle by Patent is alſo Maior of the Towne, yet doth the want of repaire thereof threaten a ſudden decay. The Pole is here eleuated to 52. 58. of Latitude, and the Longitude 20. 9. Neare <hi>Bala</hi> is a great Pond, called <hi>Pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-meare,</hi> containing 160. Acres in quantitie, which neuer by any land-flouds falling into it, is any whit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, but by ſtormes of violent winds ouerfloweth and rageth in a wonderfull manner. The <hi>Ordonices</hi> were the ancient Inhabitants of this County, who very ſtoutly oppoſed the <hi>Romanes.</hi> And after they were ſubiugated to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> (by the meanes of <hi>Owen Glendour</hi>) made many rebellious quarrels, to free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againe from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> yoake. Many Wolues in ancient times did abound in the Mountaines of this Countie, which by meanes of King <hi>Edgar</hi> were vtterly deſtroyed. The Aire here may be healthfull to the Natiues, but it is ſo continually troubled with violent winds, as it is nothing pleaſant. And the Soile ſo rough and mountainous, that though Corne can thriue there, yet for Graſſe and feeding for ſheepe, and other Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, it is no way defectiue. Herrings are caught alſo on thoſe Coaſts in abundance; and the whole Countie ſufficiently ſtored with Fiſh and Fowle.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:62"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Merionethshire</figDesc>
                     <head>MERIONYTH SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Caernarfonshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:63"/>
               <head>Carnaruon-ſhire <hi>and</hi> Angleſey.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere am I confined to a narrower limit than in the former, being to deſcribe two Prouinces in this one page. Briefly therefore thus: The <hi>Britaines</hi> called this County <hi>Caer-aruon;</hi> the Bounds whereof are <hi>Denbigh-ſhire</hi> on the Eaſt, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> on the South, the <hi>Iriſh Seas</hi> on the Weſt and North. The length from South to North containes 40 M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les, the bredth 20, and the whole compaſſe 110. There are in it 68 Pariſhes, one Biſhopricke, 17. Riuers, with 6 large Bridges. And for Commerce and Traffique 5 Market Townes, whereof the chiefeſt is the Shire-Towne <hi>Carnaruon,</hi> ſituate very pleaſantly on the Sea ſide, and encloſed with a Wall, hauing beene both beautified and fortified alſo with a ſtrong faire Caſtle, which now euen droopeth for age, and the violent force of the Sea, wherewith it is continually vndermined and battered: The Conſtable of which Caſtle (by Patent) is euer Maior; who with an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman, and two Bayliſſes, doe gouerne this Towne; where King <hi>Edward</hi> 2. was borne, and where the Pole is eleuated 53. 26. and the longitude 19. 57. The Biſhops Sea <hi>Bangor,</hi> where <hi>Hugh</hi> Earle of <hi>Cheſter</hi> built a Caſtle, is another Towne of note in this County, where the <hi>Ordo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> were the ancient Inhabitants, who by reaſon of the mountaines, (wherewith this Shire aboundeth) did long and ſtoutly withſtand the <hi>Romanes,</hi> amongſt which <hi>Snoden</hi> Hill is both the greateſt and higheſt; but for more particulars of it, and other places of note in this Shire, I muſt referre you to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Camden,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Speed,</hi> who will fully reſolue you. The Aire here is ſharp and cold; the Soile barren and hilly, and yet yeelds Milke, Butter, Cheeſe, and Hony, in a plentifull manner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="Anglesey" type="county">
               <head>Angleſey.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Romanes</hi> named this <hi>Mona,</hi> which we call <hi>Angleſey Iland,</hi> being diuided from <hi>Britaine</hi> by the Riuer <hi>Menoy,</hi> and the reſt round bounded by the Sea: it containes 20. miles in length, and 17. in bredth, the whole compaſſe being about 70. miles. Into ſix Hundreds it is diuided, and theſe are ſubdiuided into ſeuenty foure Pariſhes. It hath eight Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and but two Market Townes for Trade and Traffique, the chiefe whereof is <hi>Beau-Mariſh,</hi> built by King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, who firſt brought the whole Iland vnder the <hi>Engliſh</hi> yoke, and fortified it with a ſtrong Caſtle; the faire ſituation whereof, being in a Mooriſh place, gaue the name that it hath vnto it: which is now gouerned by a Maior annually elected, who is aſſiſted with two Bayliffes, and a Towne Clerke. The <hi>Ordouices</hi> alſo were the old Inhabitants of this Iland, who were ſubiugated to the <hi>Romanes</hi> by <hi>Julius Agricola.</hi> I reade but of one Religious Houſe in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, namely <hi>Lhaan-vais,</hi> which though it be now quite raſed, is yet memorable for the bodies of King <hi>Iohns</hi> daughter, the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Kings ſonne, the Lord <hi>Clifford,</hi> and diuers other eminent perſons there interred. The Aire is piercing, and healthfull; and though the Soile ſeeme drie and barren, yet is it plentifully ſtored with wheat, and produceth Corne and Cattell, wherewith it not only fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth it ſelfe, but is a good help to the neighbour Prouinces.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:63"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Caernarfonshire and Anglesey</figDesc>
                     <head>CARNARVAN THE ISLE OF ANGLESEY</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Denbighshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:64"/>
               <head>Denbigh-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Countie, in <hi>Britiſh</hi> called <hi>Sire Denbigh,</hi> is bounded on the Eaſt with <hi>Cheſ-ſhire</hi> and <hi>Shrop-ſhire,</hi> on the Weſt with <hi>Caernaruon</hi> and <hi>Merioneth-ſhires: Montgomery-ſhire</hi> encloſeth the South; the Sea and <hi>Flynt-ſhire</hi> the North. It ſtretcheth in length from Eaſt to Weſt one and thirty, and in bredth from South to North about ſeuenteene; the whole compaſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining much vpon an hundred and fourteene miles. Into twelue Hundreds is this Countie diſtinguiſhed, and they containe in them ſeuen and fiftie Pariſh Churches; foure and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Riuers, paſſable by ſix Bridges. And for Traffique and Trade amongſt the countrey Inhabitants, three Market Townes, whereof the Principall is the Shire Towne <hi>Denbigh,</hi> which <hi>Henry Lacy</hi> Earle of <hi>Lincolne</hi> fortified with a wall, and a ſtrong Caſtle: And yet is it famous for the faireſt place in all North-<hi>Wales.</hi> The Gouernment whereof is committed to two Aldermen, and two Bayliffes, which are euery yeare choſen out of fiue and twenty Burgeſſes, who with a Recorder and a Towne Clerke are their Aſſiſtants. The eleuation of the Pole being there 53. 18. and the Longitude 20. 51. The <hi>Ordouices</hi> were the ancient Inhabitants of this Countie, a ſtrong and warlike people, who of all others continued the longeſt free, from the <hi>Romane</hi> or <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſubiection; but firſt by <hi>Iulius Agricola</hi> to the one, and then by King <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt to the other, were ſubdued and conquered. The Vale of <hi>Cluyd</hi> being both pleaſant and fruitfull, paſſeth the ſpace of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenteene miles long, and about fiue miles broad, thorow the heart of this Shire, being walled about with high Hills, where on the top of the higheſt, called <hi>Moillenlly,</hi> was in former times entrenched a ſtrong Fort, hauing a cleare Spring of faire water. And in <hi>Llan-ſanan</hi> Pariſh, in this County, are foure and twentie ſeats cut in a circle out of a Rocke, which the Inhabitants doe call King <hi>Arthurs Round Table.</hi> The Aire is here (though ſharpe and bleake) healthfull, and the Soile in the middle moſt fruitfull: though the Eaſt and Weſt ſides are but barren and mountainous, yet yeelds it good ſtore of Sheepe, Goats, and Neat; beſides plenty of Corne, and other neceſſary Commodities.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:64"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Denbighshire</figDesc>
                     <head>DENBIGH SHIRE.</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="Flintshire" type="county">
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:65"/>
               <head>Flint-ſhire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Lint-ſhire</hi> is in forme long and narrow, being bounded on the Eaſt ſide with <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> from which it is ſeuered by the Riuer <hi>Dee,</hi> on the Weſt with <hi>Cluyd</hi> is diuided from <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigh;</hi> the South is bordered vpon by <hi>Shrop-ſhire,</hi> and the North is limited with the waues of the Sea. The length containes in all not aboue 26. Miles, and in the broadeſt part ſcarce 8. Into 5. Hundreds is it diuided, wherein are diſperſed 28 Pariſh Churches, and a Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke. With many ſmall Riuers is it well watered, but only <hi>Cluyd</hi> and <hi>Dee</hi> are two of the greateſt note. And for Commerce and Traffique, haue the Inhabitants of this County but only one Market Towne, namely <hi>Flint</hi> the Shire Towne, where <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond laid the foundation, and <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt built a faire ſtrong Caſtle, at which King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond was by <hi>Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>Northumberland</hi> circumuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſurpriſed; and by <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Duke of <hi>Hereford</hi> induced to reſigne his Crowne &amp; Royall Dignity: which when he had done, he was conueyed to the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> as a priſoner there depoſed, and afterwards at <hi>Pomfret</hi> loſt his life. The eleuation of the Pole at this place is 53. 19. and the Longitude 21. 8. The ſtout and ſturdy <hi>Ordouices,</hi> who ſo long and valiantly withſtood the <hi>Romans,</hi> were the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Inhabitants of this County, which hath beene fortified formerly with 7. faire Caſtles, which with their Hils, was a ſure and ſtrong defence againſt their enemies. At a little Towne named <hi>Halywell</hi> in this Shire, is that famous fountaine, called commonly S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Winefrids Well,</hi> of a faire Virgin of that name, who by a Lord of that Country was in that place both by force rauiſhed, and afterwards beheaded; about which Well is Moſſe growing, of a moſt odoriferous and fragrant ſmell: and ouer the ſaid Fountaine is built a faire freeſtone Chapell, in the windowes whereof is the picture of the iniured Virgin, whereto poore Pilgrimes were vſed in abundance to make their repaire. And at <hi>Kilken</hi> in this County is another little ſpring, that at certaine times doth both ebbe and ſlow like the Sea. Diuers Religious houſes haue beene ſeated in this Shire, which are now ſubuerted and turned to ruines; amongſt which that at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Aſaphs</hi> the Biſhops Sea, is memorable, for hauing 663. perſons in the brotherhood. And neare to that Monaſtery wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch was at <hi>Baſingwarke,</hi> began King <hi>Offaes</hi> Ditch, which croſſe cutteth this County: where the Aire is pleaſant, temperate and wholſome, and the Soile fruitfull, yeelding many commodities, as Corne, Graſſe, Cattell, Milke, Butter, Cheeſe, and Honey, whereof they make <hi>Metheglin:</hi> beſides which is there plenteous ſtore of Riuer Fiſh; and in ſome places good Milſtones and Grindſtones are wrought out of the Rocke.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:177548:65"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>map of Flintshire</figDesc>
                     <head>FLINT SHIRE</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177548:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
